皆さんを温かく歓迎いたします
We extend a warm welcome to one and all.
In this session, which corresponds
これから2日目午後のプログラムを
ご一緒に楽しみましょう
to the Saturday afternoon portion
of the program,
we will learn what we individually can do
人と平和な関係を築くために
一人一人に何ができるかを学びます
to pursue peace with others.
We will begin
with a music-video presentation.
では最初に
ミュージックビデオを見ましょう
The video will encourage us
to welcome others
世界的な家族に人々を迎え入れて
into our peaceful worldwide brotherhood.
平和を楽しんでもらいたいと
感じるでしょう
Please enjoy.
ご覧ください
では ご一緒に29番の歌
Please join in singing
song number 29, entitled
「エホバの証人として生きる」を
歌いましょう
“Living Up to Our Name”—song number 29.
歌は29番です
自分の不完全さによって 自分の平和や
At times, our imperfections
can disrupt our peace
人の平和が乱されることがあります
and that of others.
During the next symposium,
次のシンポジウムで
we will consider things we must avoid
平和な関係を築くために
避けなければならないことを
in order to cultivate peaceful relationships.
5つ考えます
Please give your attention
to Brother Harold Corkern,
ではまず出版委員会の援助者
a helper to the Publishing Committee,
ハロルド･コーカーン兄弟の話に
as he develops the theme
耳を傾けましょう
“‘Put Away’ Peace Wreckers
—Inappropriate Boasting.”
「平和を壊すものを『脱ぎ捨てる』
自慢」という主題です
このシンポジウムのキーワードは
What comes to your mind
when you hear the expression “put away”?
「脱ぎ捨てる」です
You may think of related expressions
関連する表現としてほかにも
such as “cast aside,” “dispose of,”
「捨て去る」とか「取り除く」とか
“discard,” “get rid of.”
「取り去る」というものがあります
クリスチャンは何を
「脱ぎ捨てる」必要がありますか
What did we have to put away
to become a Christian?
The Bible in the book
その答えは 聖書の
of Ephesians 4:22
provides the answer.
エフェソス 4:22に書かれています
エフェソス 4:22です
That’s Ephesians 4:22:
「皆さんは 古い人格を
脱ぎ捨てるようにと教えられました
“You were taught
to put away the old personality
その人格は
以前の生き方に基づくもので
“that conforms
to your former course of conduct
and that is being corrupted
according to its deceptive desires.”
悪い欲望に引きずられて
腐敗していきます」
So we had “to put away the old personality.”
私たちは「古い人格を脱ぎ捨て」ました
でも 脱ぎ捨てるだけでなく
But it’s one thing to put it away;
また身に着けないように
しなければなりません
it’s something else to keep it away.
And that’s why
in the very next verse, verse 23,
それでパウロは 次の節
23節でこう勧めています
Paul encourages us to do this:
“And you should continue to be made new
「考え方を新しくする
努力を続けましょう」
in your dominant mental attitude.”
It’s so important to keep it away,
古い人格は平和を壊してしまうので
because the old personality has traits
再び身に着けないようにすることが
that can become peace wreckers.
とても重要です
This symposium
will consider five peace wreckers
このシンポジウムでは5つ
that we should put away and keep away.
平和を壊す事柄を取り上げます
それぞれの話で取り上げられる
平和を壊すものが
Each talk will include
the following main points:
(1) It will define the peace wrecker,
まず どんなものかを学びます
2つ目に
それがどのように平和を壊すか
(2) it will explain how it wrecks peace,
and (3) we will consider how to put it away.
3つ目に それをどのように
脱ぎ捨てるかを考えます
What is the very first one
that we’re going to talk about?
まず最初に取り上げるのは何でしょうか
それは 自慢することです
It is inappropriate boasting.
What is inappropriate boasting?
自慢とは何でしょうか
Basically, it’s self-praise,
自分を称賛することです
and the Bible condemns self-praise
そのことについて 格言 27:2には
Notice Proverbs 27:2:
「自分の口ではなく
別の人があなたを称賛するようにせよ
“Let someone else praise you,
自分の唇ではなくほかの人たちが」と
書かれています
“and not your own mouth;
others, and not your own lips.”
自分を称賛することは誇りの表れで
Self-praise is an evidence of pride
that causes one
to elevate himself above others.
自分をほかの人よりも
高めていることになります
Some might develop an unhealthy pride
宣教で得られた成果を含め
about their accomplishments,
even in the ministry.
自分の成し遂げたことを
誇る人もいます
1世紀にはどんなことが
あったでしょうか
It happened in the first century.
Paul had to write
to the Corinthian congregation
パウロは コリントの会衆の
兄弟姉妹の間で不和が生じ
about the dissensions that they were having,
平和が損なわれていることを
指摘しました
the lack of peace they were experiencing.
Why?
会衆の中に「思い上がって」いる
人たちがいたからです
Well, some in the congregation
were “puffed up with pride” about themselves
自分はパウロに従う アポロに従う
or other men,
such as Paul, Apollos, Cephas.
ケファに従う という人たちもいました
They were giving
too much attention to themselves
自分や他の人に
過度の注意を向けていたのです
and to other men.
今も同じようなことが生じ得ます
Well, how could that happen today?
Well, let’s imagine
a group of brothers talking,
兄弟姉妹がおしゃべりをしている時に
1人がこう言います
and one in the group says,
「よく祈って頑張ったら
“With Jehovah’s help
and with diligent prayer and effort,
エホバのおかげで
聖書レッスンが見つかったんです」
I finally got a Bible study.”
But right away,
another one in the group proudly declares,
するとすかさず 別の人がこう言います
「私は4人と勉強していて
2人は集会に来ていて
“I have four Bible studies;
two are attending meetings,
and one will soon be baptized.”
1人はもうすぐバプテスマなんです」
Could such a statement be a peace wrecker?
平和が壊れてしまうのでは
ないでしょうか
確かに 自慢すると
平和が壊れてしまいます
How does inappropriate boasting
wreck peace?
宣教を楽しむのも 良い成果が
得られた時にエホバに感謝するのも
Well, it’s not wrong
to take pleasure in our work
and to thank Jehovah
for the success that we may have.
悪いことではありません
でも 自分の成し遂げたことを
自慢すると
But inappropriate boasting
about our accomplishments
競争心やねたみや対抗心を
あおってしまいます
can stir up competition, envy, and rivalry.
We must remember that self-promotion
自分をアピールすることは
「平和の神」エホバからの
ものではありません
does not originate
with our heavenly Father, “the God of peace.”
どこから出るものでしょうか
Where does it originate?
ヨハネ第一 2:16にはこうあります
First John 2:16 says:
“The showy display of one’s means of life
「持ち物を見せびらかすことは皆
父からのものではなく
“does not originate with the Father,
but originates with the world.”
世から出るものだからです」
And would you not agree
that the world is filled with self-praise?
世の中には 自分をアピールする人が
大勢いるのではないでしょうか
Even on their social media, we see this.
SNSでもそういう人を見掛けます
Some of the material
that people post on social media
自分に注目してもらうために
いろいろな写真や動画をアップします
is designed to make one
appear very important.
And it is a showy display
自分の成し遂げたことや持ち物や
of their accomplishments,
their material possessions,
ぜいたくな旅行の様子を投稿し
or their expensive vacations that they enjoy.
見せびらかします
「私を見て いいでしょ？」と
いうわけです
In other words, it’s all about “look at me.”
自分をアピールすることは
平和を壊す 世の精神です
Well, we want to avoid getting caught up
in the world’s spirit of self-promotion
そういう精神に
染まらないようにしましょう
that wrecks peace.
平和を壊すものである自慢は
To illustrate just how devastating
the peace wrecker’s
inappropriate boasting can be,
どれほど悲惨な結果に
つながるでしょうか
let’s briefly consider
the Bible character Haman.
聖書に出てくるハマンの例を
考えましょう
ハマンはプライドが高く
He was a proud and haughty man,
高慢で 自慢ばかりしていました
and he boasted a lot.
Esther chapter 5 tells us
エステル 5章によると
ハマンは家族や友人に
that he was boasting
with his family and friends
自分の富のこと 多くの息子のこと
about his wealth, his many sons,
how the king had promoted him
to a high station,
王が自分を他の家来たちより
高い地位に就けたこと
that he was above all the other servants,
and that he’d had a special meal, or banquet,
王と王妃に宴会に招かれたことを
自慢しました
with the king and queen.
ハマンは傲慢な悪人でした
But Haman was hateful and arrogant.
エホバに仕える人モルデカイを
殺そうとしました
And he was plotting to kill
Jehovah’s faithful servant Mordecai.
But his scheme
and his attitudes were exposed.
やがて ハマンの正体とたくらみが
暴露されます
And what happened?
The very stake that Haman had built
モルデカイを掛けようとして
用意した杭に
to hang Mordecai on he was hung on.
自分が掛けられたのです
この出来事について考えると
And it reminds us
—doesn’t it?—
that at Isaiah 29:20, the Bible says:
イザヤ 29:20の
次の言葉を思い出します
“The boaster will come to his finish.”
「自慢する者は終わりを迎え［る］」
自慢することが 自分や他の人に
どれほど悪い影響を与えるかを考えると
So because of the devastating effects
that improper boasting
can have on ourselves and others,
we do not even want
to give the impression of boasting.
私たちは 自慢しているという
印象さえ与えたくありません
次のビデオをご覧ください
In the following dramatization,
notice how a sister’s actions
ある姉妹の言動が
are misunderstood as boasting.
自慢と受け止められてしまいます
“Put away from yourselves every kind
「あらゆる悪意 怒り 憤り わめき
“of malicious bitterness, anger, wrath,
“screaming, and abusive speech,
暴言など 一切の有害な事柄を
捨て去ってください」
as well as everything injurious.”
朝起きて 「今日はあの兄弟に
Did anyone start the day thinking,
‘I believe I’ll show malicious bitterness
to my brother today’?
悪意のある言葉を言ってやろう」と
思った人がいますか
いないでしょう でも
意図せずそうなることはありますね
Of course not!
And yet the potential is there, isn’t it?
平和を壊さない鍵は 心からの愛です
But genuine affection fights peace wreckers.
And affection grows when we really know
our brothers and sisters well.
兄弟姉妹のことをよく知れば
愛は強くなります
We remember their joys
兄弟姉妹が経験している喜びや痛み
and pains,
熱い思い
their selfless zeal,
how they came to love Jehovah,
エホバに引き寄せられたこと
耐えていることなどをよく考えましょう
and what they endure.
分かった すぐ帰る じゃあね
ああ 大変
I’ll get back as soon as I can.
Love you. Bye.
Oh, no!
ヘイリー！
Haley, love?
あっ 行かなきゃいけなくて
So sorry, I’ve got to run.
オッケー 後で電話する
OK. I’ll ring you about this week.
ありがと またね
またね またね
Thanks. Love you both.
See you!
The afternoon would look better.
午後の方が良さそう
おばあちゃん！
あらまあヘイリー
Nana!
Hello, Haley, darling.
I’m so, so sorry.
ほんとにごめんなさいね
全然大丈夫
Oh, it’s not too bad.
I’ve got this.
片付けるね
ああ
Oh.
大丈夫だった？
ありがとう 悪いね
How are you though?
Thank you. I’m so sorry.
Oh, poor thing.
いいのよ ちょっと待ってて
Let me clear this up.
ありがとう
Thank you.
Oh, Nana, it’s Sunday today, isn’t it?
おばあちゃん 今日日曜日だから
This one.
こっちだね
今日もいろいろあったもんね
It’s felt like such a long day, hasn’t it?
ほんとにそうね
It has felt like a long day.
Thanks.
おやすみなさい
Sleep well.
Hello, everyone.
皆さんこんにちは
デミュアデザインのヘイリーです
Haley from DeNure Design here,
helping you to be effortlessly elegant.
さりげないおしゃれを日常に
初めての方も いつも見てくれている
方も 見てくれてありがとうございます
I want to welcome my new followers
and thank everyone
for subscribing to this channel.
初めに紹介するのは このかわいい
ピアスとネックレスのセットです
So first up, I’ve got
this gorgeous earring and necklace set.
And as you can see, the first disc I’ve done
is in this warm nude tone,
淡い色で作ってみたので どんな色の
お洋服にも似合うと思います
and that’s great because it goes . . .
ちょっとこれ見てよ
Can you believe her?
形もかわいいし
質感もとてもいいですよ
Haley’s business feed?
仕事でやってるやつでしょ
セットで着けると
とってもおしゃれです
But what makes this set is really special.
It’s giving you
that understated elegant look.
主張し過ぎないけど
大人っぽさをプラス！
If you haven’t done so already,
please hit the subscribe button below.
まだの方は チャンネル登録も
よろしくお願いします
Because as you know,
着けるとこんな感じ すてきでしょ？
when you look this good, you feel great.
ビデオの姉妹は
あからさまに自慢していたでしょうか
Was the sister in this video
boasting inappropriately?
いいえ 姉妹はエホバに仕える
謙遜な人です
No, she was a humble servant of Jehovah,
kindly and patiently
helping her elderly relative.
祖母を優しく世話することもしています
But do you recall her business website
でも 仕事で作っている
アクセサリーを紹介する動画で
and the presentation she made
about her jewelry products?
何と言っていましたか
こう言っていました
She said,
「着けるとこんな感じ
すてきでしょ？」
“When you look this good,
you feel great.”
動画を見たある姉妹は心を乱され
Her Christian sister was upset
and took those comments and her actions
その姉妹が自慢していると感じました
to be boastful.
Well, this video reminds us
自分の言葉や行動が
to think about how our words and our actions
人にどう受け止められるかを
考えることは大切です
may appear to others.
So now we’re going to get to the question:
では 自慢という平和を壊すものを
どのように脱ぎ捨てられるでしょうか
How do we put away inappropriate boasting?
A key point that we must always remember
心に留めておくべき大切な点が
to help us to do just that
is recorded in the book
コリント第一 4:7に書かれています
of 1 Corinthians 4:7,
コリント第一 4:7です
1 Corinthians 4:7:
こうあります
「あなたの何が他の人より
優れているのですか
“For who makes you different from another?
“Indeed, what do you have
that you did not receive?
あなたが持っているもので
もらったのではないものがあるのですか
“If, in fact, you did receive it,
もらったのであれば
why do you boast
as though you did not receive it?”
どうしてもらったのではないかのように
誇るのですか」
What’s the point of this scripture?
ポイントは何でしょうか
We do not want to boast about ourselves
自慢するのではなく
自分の成し遂げたことは
全てエホバのおかげだと認めることです
but give all credit to Jehovah
for the good that we can do.
Now, some people are proud
about their good looks,
人々はいろいろなことを誇ります
外見や 人気や 富や 地位や
their popularity,
their wealth, their position,
身体能力や 音楽の才能などです
their physical strength,
their musical ability.
古代イスラエルのダビデ王は
But remember, King David of ancient Israel
その全てを持っていました
had all of those assets.
But throughout his entire life,
でもダビデは 自慢することは
ありませんでした
he never became a boastful person.
He remained humble.
いつも謙遜でした なぜでしょうか
Why?
詩編 113:5-8で
At Psalm 113:5-8,
David gave all credit to Jehovah.
ダビデはエホバに注意を向けています
He said that in his case
Jehovah stooped down
「立場が低い」自分のために
身をかがめ 地面から引き上げて
and took this “lowly” one
and raised him up
「高貴な人たちと共に座」らせて
くださったと言っています
to “sit with nobles.”
またダビデは いろいろな機会に
And on every occasion that he had,
David would always say, ‘Praise Jehovah,
「エホバを賛美せよ」とか
「神の聖なる名を誇れ」と言っています
boast about his holy name.’
Well, we, like David,
should “boast in Jehovah.”
私たちもエホバを誇りとすべきです
パウロも コリント第一 1:31で
こう勧めています
The apostle Paul encouraged us to do that
at 1 Corinthians 1:31:
“The one who boasts,
let him boast in Jehovah.”
「誇る人はエホバについて
誇るべきです」
どういう意味でしょうか
What does that mean?
真の神を知っていること
エホバの望むことを行うため
It means that we boast in the privilege
of knowing the true God
and of being able
to be used by him to accomplish his will.
エホバに使っていただけることを
誇るのです
自慢しないためにできることが
ほかにもあります
Now, another way
that we can put away improper boasting
自分のことばかり話すのではなく
is to not talk about ourselves,
but to acknowledge the good
and the fine qualities
仲間の良いところや
良い行いについて話すことです
that our fellow workers have.
Humble and modest people
don’t brag about what they do,
謙遜で慎み深い人は
自分のしたことについて
誇ったりしません
but they turn their attention
to their fellow workers
むしろエホバが兄弟姉妹を
どのように用い
and see how Jehovah is using them
and blessing them in his service.
祝福しているかに注意を向けます
And when we do that,
そうすれば 雰囲気はとても和やかで
that creates a very peaceful,
happy environment.
平和なものになるでしょう
それでは 自慢という
平和を壊すものを脱ぎ捨て
Well, may we continue
to put away and keep away
inappropriate boasting—self-praise.
また身に着けないようにしましょう
そのために 何を成し遂げるとしても
How?
By giving praise and thanks and honor
to Jehovah for our accomplishments
エホバを賛美したいと思います
and by commending our fellow workers
for all the good qualities they have
そして 仲間の良いところを褒め
エホバが仲間をどう用いているかに
注意を向けましょう
and for how Jehovah
is using them in his service.
By doing so, we will preserve
our precious possession of peace
そうすれば 貴重な平和を
守ることができます
エホバとも 兄弟姉妹ともです
with Jehovah and with our brothers.
奉仕委員会の援助者
セス･ハイアット兄弟が
Brother Seth Hyatt,
a helper to the Service Committee,
シンポジウムの次の話をします
will now present
the next talk of this symposium,
主題は「平和を壊すものを
『脱ぎ捨てる』 ねたみ」です
“‘Put Away’ Peace Wreckers—Envy.”
What is envy?
ねたみとは何でしょうか
Do you know?
ねたみがどんなふうに表れるかを
知っておくことは大切です
It’s important that we be able to identify
the symptoms of envy.
なぜでしょうか
Why?
Because envy is an expression
of hatred.
ねたみは憎しみの一種だからです
平和を壊すものです
It’s an enemy of peace.
And if left unchecked,
注意していないと
エホバとの関係も壊れてしまいます
it can result in spiritual death.
As described in the Bible,
envy has two symptoms.
聖書によれば ねたみには
2つの症状があるといえます
1つ目はすぐ思い付く症状です
The first is probably more familiar.
An envious person wants
それは 人が持っているものを
欲しがることです
what someone else has.
It’s the second symptom
でもねたみには もう一つの
症状があるので 非常に厄介です
that makes envy especially dangerous.
その症状とは 人の持っているものを
欲しがるだけでなく
An envious person not only wants
what someone else has,
それをその人に持って
ほしくないと思うことです
but he also doesn’t want
the other person to have it.
例を考えましょう
Here’s an example:
In the first century,
Jewish religious leaders envied Jesus
1世紀にユダヤ人の宗教指導者たちは
イエスをねたみました
イエスが人々に好かれていたからです
because Jesus was much appreciated
by the common people.
Jesus dealt with people,
イエスは立場の低い人たちを含め
including lowly ones,
in a way that dignified them.
人々に敬意を持って接していました
それで 多くの人に愛されました
As a result, he was appreciated.
宗教指導者たちはねたみました
The religious leaders envied him.
人々に対する自分たちの
接し方を変えるのではなく
But rather than adjusting their own way
of dealing with people,
they attacked Jesus verbally
イエスのことを悪く言いました
in an effort to destroy
his good reputation.
イエスの評判を落とそうとしたのです
中傷し 悪いうわさを広めました
They spread malicious slander.
つまり イエスが持っていたものを
欲しがっただけでなく
Not only did they want
what Jesus had,
それをイエスに持たせたく
なかったのです
but also they didn’t want
Jesus to have it.
ねたみは ガラテア 5:21で
No wonder envy is listed
as one of “the works of the flesh”
「罪深い欲望から出る行い」の
1つに挙げられています
at Galatians 5:21.
ねたみはとても危険なので
It’s a dangerous quality
何としても避けたいと思います
that we need to avoid.
ねたみはどのように
平和を壊すのでしょうか
How does envy disrupt peace?
ねたみは家族や会衆の絆を弱め
Envy undermines, damages,
or even destroys relationships
やがてその絆を破壊してしまいます
in the family and in the congregation.
Consider the example of Jacob
ヤコブと12人の息子の事を
考えてみましょう
and his 12 sons.
Jacob had special affection
for one of his sons, Joseph.
ヤコブは息子のヨセフを
特別に愛していました
それで兄たちはねたむようになりました
As a result,
Joseph’s brothers became envious.
How did the envy manifest itself?
彼らのねたみはどのような形で
表れたでしょうか
What was the fruitage?
兄たちはヨセフにつらく当たり
奴隷として売ってしまいました
Well, they dealt treacherously
with Joseph, selling him into slavery.
And as if that weren’t bad enough,
they compounded their wrong
それだけでなく
ヤコブにうそをつきました
by lying to Jacob,
「ヨセフは死んでしまった」
telling him that Joseph was dead.
そう報告したのです
According to the Bible account,
家族が慰めようとしても
Jacob “refused to be comforted.”
ヤコブは聞こうとしませんでした
ヨセフの死を何年も悲しみました
He mourned Joseph for years.
What a terrible consequence of envy!
ねたみは悲惨な結果につながりました
It’s clear that envy
こうした結果から分かる通り
ねたみの気持ちを抱いていると
allows no room for love,
愛や親切や思いやりが
影を潜めてしまいます
compassion, or kindness.
Those qualities go out the window.
その代わりに 憎しみや敵意や
And they’re replaced by qualities
such as hatred, strife, fits of anger.
怒りなどを表すようになってしまいます
では 会衆への影響についても
考えてみましょう
Can envy disrupt the peace
of a congregation?
コラ ダタン アビラムの事を
思い出してください
Consider the examples
of Korah, Dathan, and Abiram.
They envied Moses and Aaron
彼らはイスラエルの民の中での
モーセとアロンの立場をねたみました
in the congregation of Israel.
ねたみはどんな形で表れたでしょうか
How did that envy manifest itself?
エホバから任命された2人について
批判的なことを言いました
Well, they began
to speak negatively—critically—
of Jehovah’s representatives,
even accusing Moses
モーセを非難し 「エホバの会衆に
of playing the prince
and lifting himself up above the others.
君臨しようとしている」
とまで言いました
They forgot that Jehovah
モーセとアロンに責任を委ねたのが
had put Moses and Aaron
in their positions of responsibility.
エホバである という事実を
見失っていたことが分かります
How did Jehovah react
それを見ていたエホバは
to that manifestation of envy?
どう行動したでしょうか
3人とその反逆に加わった人たちを
滅ぼしました
He destroyed those three men
and all who supported them.
For a time, the congregation
was robbed of its peace,
当時のイスラエルの会衆の
平和が失われてしまったのです
and the accounts
certainly provide some insight
こうした記述から エホバがねたみを
どう見ているかが分かります
into Jehovah’s view of envy.
Now, by this point,
you’re no doubt thinking,
でも こう思うかもしれません
‘I would never want something
so badly that I would
「私は相手を傷つけてまで
その人の持っているものを
奪おうなんて思わない」
damage someone else to get it.’
でも 私たちは不完全です
But we’re all imperfect.
We have a treacherous heart,
心は信用できないので
気付かないうちにねたむことがあります
and envy is insidious.
ドラマの続きを見てみましょう
In the following dramatization,
notice how envy
threatens to disrupt peace.
ねたみによって 平和が
どのように脅かされるでしょうか
また？
どうしたの？
Really?
Bad news?
あ ヘイリー かわいいじゃない
She’s a sweetie.
そうだ ネックレス
買おうと思ってたんだった
It reminds me that I want to speak to her
about a necklace.
え 姉妹も？やり過ぎだと思いません？
You too?
You don’t think she’s showing off?
そんなことないわよ
No.
Everyone thinks she’s “Miss Wonderful”;
みんなヘイリーの話ばっかり
ヘイリーもまんざらでもなさそう
she’s starting to agree.
Is this just about Haley?
ヘイリーが悪いってこと？
It seems it’s all about Haley.
私はそう思ったんですけど
お茶が冷めちゃう
Your tea is getting cold.
And you’re changing the subject.
話そらすんですね
No,
そうじゃないけど
but you’ve brought this up before.
前もその話 してたよね
What is it?
どうしたの？
ヘイリーは一緒に開拓してる友達でしょ
You’re friends; you pioneer together.
Yeah, and that’s why I’m concerned.
だから心配してるんです
Concern is good,
心配してあげるのはいいことだけど
but
is there just a little bit of envy in there?
ちょっとねたんでるところない？
エミリーはどんな様子でしたか
What did you notice?
Well, Emily is suffering
from an onset of envy.
ねたみの気持ちが
心に芽生えていましたね
Did you notice
how she questioned Haley’s motives
ヘイリーの動機を疑っているようでした
and potentially called
Haley’s reputation into question?
ヘイリーの評判を下げてしまうような
ことを言っていました
こういうことは誰にでも起きます
It could happen to any one of us.
So how do we battle and conquer envy?
ねたみの気持ちに
負けないようにするには
どうしたらよいでしょうか
By cultivating two beautiful qualities,
私たちにできる2つのことがあります
謙遜になることと 満足することです
humility and contentment.
Let’s see what the Bible
has to say about humility.
まず 聖書が謙遜さについて
何と述べているか見てみましょう
Turn with me, please,
to Philippians chapter 2,
フィリピ 2章をご覧ください
and we’re going to begin reading
in verse 3
3節から読みます
—Philippians 2:3:
フィリピ 2:3
“Do nothing out of contentiousness
「対抗心を抱いたり 自己中心的に
なったりしてはなりません」
or out of egotism.”
自己中心的な人は
What is egotism?
自分のことを実際以上に
優れていると考えがちです
Well, it’s having
an exaggerated opinion of oneself.
Do you think that the religious leaders
in Jesus’ day,
イエスの時代の宗教指導者たちや
ヨセフの兄たちや
Joseph’s brothers,
コラ ダタン アビラムは
Korah, Dathan, and Abiram
had this affliction?
まさにそういう人たちでした
Did they have an exaggerated view
of themselves?
そう思いませんか
でも 他人事ではありません
Without question!
But it’s an affliction
that could affect any one of us.
誰にでもそうなってしまう
危険があります
どうしたらいいでしょうか
What is the solution?
Well, Paul continues:
聖句の続きを見てみましょう
“But with humility [or, lowliness of mind]
「謙遜になり 自分より他の人の方が
上だと考えてください」
consider others superior to you”
—or consider others
つまり 自分より他の人の方が
重要だと考えるのです
as more important than yourself.
Now, that kind of mindset
そう考える人は
次のアドバイスに従います
allows a person to do what’s stated
in verse 4:
4節です
“As you look out not only
「自分のことばかり考えずに
“for your own interests,
but also for the interests of others.”
他の人のことにも気を配りましょう」
A humble person
謙遜であれば 人のことに気を配ります
looks out for others.
He doesn’t feel that he deserves
自分の方が人より重要だとは考えません
more than others.
満足することも大切です
Contentment—a content person
is satisfied with what he has.
持っているもので満足します
奉仕の立場や割り当て
He doesn’t compare
his privilege or his possession
持っているものについて
with another person’s privilege
or possession.
自分をほかの人と比較しません
満足しているからです
He’s content.
謙遜であり 満足するなら
Humility, contentment
—with Jehovah’s help we can cultivate
these beautiful qualities—
人をねたむことはないでしょう
エホバに助けてもらいながら
qualities that leave no room for envy.
ねたみという平和を壊すものを
脱ぎ捨てましょう
And in doing so, we promote peace
そうするなら 自分自身
穏やかな気持ちになり
—inner peace, peace in our family,
家庭にも会衆にも
平和をつくることができます
and peace in the congregation.
And you can be sure
that Jehovah appreciates that.
エホバは心から喜んでくださるでしょう
出版委員会の援助者
ガイユス･グロッケンティン兄弟が
Brother Gajus Glockentin,
a helper to the Publishing Committee,
will now present the next talk
of this symposium,
シンポジウムの次の話を
してくださいます
主題は「平和を壊すものを
『脱ぎ捨てる』 不正直」
“‘Put Away’ Peace Wreckers—Dishonesty.”
What comes to your mind
when you hear the word “dishonesty”?
不正直と聞くと誰を思い出しますか
「うその根源」と呼ばれている
サタンでしょうか
Maybe you think of Satan,
“the father of the lie.”
あるいは アナニアと
妻のサッピラですか
Or Ananias and his wife come to your mind.
2人はうそをついたために
命を失いました
They lost their lives because of lying.
We do not want to imitate such ones.
サタンやこの2人のような
うそつきにはなりたくありません
We avoid lying.
Is that, though, as far as our honesty goes?
では あからさまなうそをつかなければ
それでいいのでしょうか
Our holy God, Jehovah,
wants us to be holy as well,
聖なる神エホバはご自分の民に
聖なる人であってほしいと願っています
and that is why he urged
the ancient Israelites
それで 人を「だましてはなら」ないと
命じています
not to deceive others
as mentioned at Leviticus 19:11.
レビ記 19:11にある通りです
ここから正直さについて何が学べますか
Does this not add some color to honesty?
正直さには人をだまさないこと
Dishonesty includes
(and please take note of this definition)
つまり相手に間違った印象を
与えるようなことを
intentionally leading someone
to a wrong conclusion.
意図的に言わないことが含まれます
例えば 事実をゆがめたり
For example, by twisting the truth
or by providing only certain details,
都合のいいことだけを言ったりするなら
他の人との平和が損なわれます
we endanger our peace with others.
Why can we say so?
なぜそう言えますか
How does dishonesty wreck peace?
不正直によって どのように
平和は壊れてしまうでしょうか
Peace and a peaceful relationship
平和や良い関係は
信頼の上に築かれます
are built on trust.
Trusting someone makes you feel
safe and secure
信頼できる人と一緒にいると
心地よく 安心できます
and puts you at ease.
There is no peace without trust.
信頼のないところに平和はありません
信頼はどのように築かれますか
How do we develop trust?
Trust is the result
of spending time together,
一緒に過ごし 互いに真実を
語ることによって築かれます
speaking the truth with one another.
私たちが信頼するのは
聖書が言う「不正直な話し方」
We trust people who act unselfishly
and do not use “crooked speech,”
as the Bible puts it.
「曲がった話し方」をしない人です
誰かが一度でも不正直な話し方をすると
If someone deceives us only once
or is dishonest in another way,
その人の話は全て信じられなく
なってしまうかもしれません
we might start to question
everything they say.
One single act of dishonesty may be enough.
たった一度不正直な話し方をしただけで
評判が傷ついてしまうのです
It can ruin their reputation.
それだけではありません
As bad as this is,
dishonesty has the potential
場合によっては
もっと深刻な問題につながります
to create even greater damage.
Dishonesty can be compared
不正直は 感染力の強い
ウイルスのようです
with a highly contagious virus.
Dishonesty breeds dishonesty.
不正直というウイルスは
他の人にうつります
People who have contact
with deceitful, dishonest persons
不正直な人に接していると
自分もそのウイルスに
感染してしまうかもしれません
are in danger of being infected.
Dishonesty might not only wreck
one relationship
その被害は 相手との
人間関係だけにとどまりません
but multiple relationships,
連鎖的に広まって
putting the unity and peace
of the whole group at risk.
みんなの平和と一致が
損なわれてしまうことがあるのです
聖書の創世記に出てくる
This reminds us of the relationship
ラバンとヤコブとの間で起きた
出来事を思い出します
between Laban and Jacob
in the Bible book of Genesis.
ヤコブはラバンとの約束に基づいて
Based on the agreement with Laban,
7年間一生懸命働きました
Jacob worked hard for seven years
娘のラケルと結婚するためです
in order to marry Laban’s daughter Rachel.
And despite this high price
that Jacob had to pay,
ヤコブは7年という
長い期間にわたって働きましたが
ラケルを深く愛していたので
those years seemed for him
「ほんの数日」のように思いました
just like “a few days.”
ところが 妻として与えられたのは
ラケルではなく 姉のレアでした
Sadly, instead of Rachel,
he received the older daughter, Leah,
as a wife.
So now Leah was also part of the deception.
ですから レアもヤコブを
だましていたことになります
What was the result after Jacob had found out
ラバンにだまされたことを知った
ヤコブはどう思ったでしょうか
that Laban tricked him?
裏切られたと感じ ラバンのことを
信用できなくなったでしょう
The trust was gone.
The relationship had suffered
to a great degree.
不正直によって人間関係や
平和が壊れてしまったのです
Dishonesty wrecked the peace
in those relationships,
and so the following seven years
of work for Rachel were bitter.
しかもその後 ラケルのために
もう7年働かなければなりませんでした
ラバンの不正直なやり方は
その後もまだまだ続きます
And Laban’s dishonesty emboldened him
to continue in his course.
He unfairly changed Jacob’s wages ten times.
不当にも ヤコブの報酬を
10回も変えました
He deceived Jacob.
ヤコブをだましたのです
Because of Laban’s dishonesty,
ラバンが不正直だったため
家族全体の平和が壊れてしまいました
the peace in the whole family
was disrupted.
Let us now continue to watch
the next segment of the dramatization.
ではこれから ドラマの続く部分を
見てみましょう
We left Emily and Celia sitting
in a coffee shop.
エミリーとセリアはカフェにいました
Please watch carefully, and notice
エミリーがどのように
真実をゆがめているか
how Emily is tempted to alter the truth.
注意深くご覧ください
ヘイリーは一緒に開拓してる友達でしょ
You pioneer together.
I know, and that’s why I’m concerned.
だから心配してるんです
Concern is good,
心配してあげるのはいいことだけど
but
is there just a little bit of envy in there?
ちょっとねたんでるところない？
分かってくれると思ってたのに
I thought you would understand.
あなたが感じていることは分かるわよ
I think I understand your feelings.
でもヘイリーのことは？
But not about Haley?
I haven’t seen all her posts.
全部を見たわけじゃないけど
何か不道徳な投稿があったの？
There’s nothing immoral, is there?
No.
ないですけど
良かった そんなはずないよね
Good. That’s not like her.
でも もし限度を
超えているっていうことなら
Now, if
it’s a case of her being more careful
how she comes across,
話は別だけどね
that’s another matter.
Why don’t you talk to her?
ヘイリーと話してみたら？
そうですね
Maybe.
Emily, you are a beautiful, spiritual sister.
エミリー あなたはよく頑張っていて
とてもすてきな姉妹よ
You know,
あのね
私も長いこと
for years,
人と比べてしまう
傾向があったんだけどね
I had a bad habit
of comparing myself to others.
そのせいで自分も傷ついたし
My own insecurity hurt me
友達も傷つけちゃったの
and my closest friends.
セリア姉妹に話さなければ
よかったってこと？
So you don’t think
I should’ve spoken to Celia?
No, I’m glad you asked Celia about it
いや 話してよかったと思うよ
信頼できる姉妹だしね
—someone you trust.
姉妹は何て？
What did she say?
Well, she definitely understands how I feel.
「すごくよく分かる」って言ってくれた
良かったね
Good.
And about Haley’s posts?
ヘイリーの動画のことは？
Well, she hasn’t seen
everything she has out there.
うーん
「全部は見てない」って言ってたけど
Hmm.
うーん
「限度を超えてるから
She did say that Haley
ヘイリーは もっと
気を付けなきゃいけない」って
needs to be more careful
how she comes across.
姉妹も言ってた
何かアドバイスくれた？
What did she suggest?
That I should tell her
that she needs to stop,
「やめるように言った方がいい」って
言われた
but I’m too worked up.
でもそんなの無理！
Look,
ねえ
if Celia agrees
that Haley is doing something she shouldn’t,
セリア姉妹がそんなふうに
言ってるんだったら
ヘイリーと話した方がいいよ
you should talk to her.
きっと話すタイミングがあるよ
You’ll find the right time.
分かってくれてありがとう
Thanks for understanding.
I’m hungry.
おなかすいた 祈ってくれる？
Can you say the prayer?
よし
Sure.
Jehovah, we’d like to praise you
エホバ 親切に今日の夕飯を
与えてくださり 感謝します ・・・
for your generosity and kindness . . .
エミリーは自分の都合のいいように
話を聞いていましたね
Did you notice how Emily just heard
what she wanted to hear?
In talking to her husband, Jake,
she painted an incomplete picture.
夫のジェイクに話す時には
いくらか脚色していました
セリアは実際には
ヘイリーの投稿について
She did not relay that Celia had no opinion
about the social media posts of Haley.
いいとも悪いとも言っていませんでした
また 「ヘイリーに投稿をやめるように
言ったら」とも言いませんでした
And contrary to what she told her husband,
Celia did not encourage her
to tell Haley to stop.
必要なら話し合うよう勧めただけです
仲間には真実を語るべきです
Our brothers and sisters deserve the truth.
でもエミリーは事実をゆがめました
不正直でした
But Emily didn’t relay that, did she?
She was dishonest, something that can have
後で分かりますが
大きな問題に発展します
a damaging effect, as we will see later.
エホバは 不正直という平和を壊すもの
を脱ぎ捨てるようにと言っています
Jehovah wants us to put away
this peace wrecker, dishonesty.
He wants us to always be truthful,
私たちがいつでも正直であることを
望んでいます
even in small matters.
小さなことでもです
Therefore, how do we put away dishonesty?
では どうすれば不正直を
脱ぎ捨てられますか
まず 正直でなければならない
理由に注目しましょう
Let us please turn to Ephesians chapter 4.
Here the apostle Paul reminds us
エフェソス 4章にある
パウロの言葉を見てみたいと思います
of a reason to be honest.
This is Ephesians chapter 4,
エフェソス 4:25です
and we want to read verse 25:
こうあります
“Therefore, now that you
have put away deceit,
「皆さんは偽りを捨て去ったのですから
“each one of you speak truth
with his neighbor,
隣人に真実を語りましょう
私たちは皆で1つの体を
構成しているのです」
because we are members
belonging to one another.”
Did you notice why we put away deceit
偽りを捨て去り
互いに真実を語るべきなのはなぜですか
and speak truth with one another?
Paul says: “Because we are
members belonging to one another.”
「私たちは皆で1つの体を
構成している」からです
不正直は 同じ体を構成している
兄弟姉妹に悪い影響を与えます
In other words, Paul reminds us of the fact
that dishonesty affects others
—our brothers and our relationship with them.
信頼関係も損なわれてしまいます
So, then, knowing this,
不正直を脱ぎ捨てるべき理由が
よく分かりました
how can we put away dishonesty?
では 脱ぎ捨てるには
どうしたらいいですか
The answer is:
By considering the consequences
of dishonesty and honesty.
正直であることと不正直であることの
結果を考えることです
This will help us to do the right thing.
それが大きな助けになります
まず 不正直がどんな結果に
なるかを考えましょう
Now, what are the consequences of dishonesty?
As we’ve seen in the case of Laban and Jacob,
ラバンとヤコブの例から分かる通り
他の人との平和な関係が
壊れてしまいます
it will disrupt the peace with others.
And since Jehovah hates dishonesty,
またエホバは不正直を憎んでいるので
it will also disrupt our peace with Jehovah.
エホバとの平和な関係も
壊れてしまいます
On the other hand,
逆に 正直であることは
どんな結果につながりますか
what are the consequences of honesty?
不正直な言い方をすれば その場を
うまく切り抜けられるかもしれません
While dishonesty might seem in the moment
to be the easier way out,
in the long run,
でも長い目で見ると
honesty will enable us to have good friends.
正直であれば良い友を
作ることができます
They want to enjoy peace as well,
平和な関係を楽しみたいと
思っている人は
and therefore they are also searching
信頼できる人を友にしたいと
思っています
for someone they can trust.
And in this way, we are
信頼関係を築ければ
like ‘body members belonging to one another.’
体の各器官である私たちは一致できます
さらに大切な点として
And even more important,
we will enjoy a good conscience
晴れ晴れとした良心を持ち
「神との平和」を楽しむことができます
and “peace with God.”
Let us, therefore, put away
this peace wrecker (dishonesty)
ですから 平和を壊すものである
不正直を脱ぎ捨てましょう
by sticking to the truth
even in small things.
小さなことでも
正直であるようにしましょう
Dear brothers and sisters, Jehovah knows
不完全な私たちにとって
これが簡単ではないことを
that for us imperfect humans
エホバはよくご存じです
this is not always easy.
Yet, he promises to help us
でも私たちを助けてくれます
and to bless every step we take
では 信頼と平和を築き
壊さないようにしましょう
to build trust and peace
そうすればエホバは 私たちの努力を
祝福してくださるでしょう
and not to wreck it.
人事委員会の援助者
パトリック･ラフランカ兄弟が
Brother Patrick LaFranca,
a helper to the Personnel Committee,
シンポジウムの次の話をします
will now present
the next talk of this symposium,
主題は「平和を壊すものを
『脱ぎ捨てる』
“‘Put Away’ Peace Wreckers—Harmful Gossip.”
悪いうわさ話」です
あなたはうわさ話をしますか
Do you gossip?
No.
誰かについて話をすることは
Well, whenever we share
any news about others,
うわさ話の一種です
that is a form of gossip.
私たちは人に関心があるので
こう言うかもしれません
Because we are interested in others,
we might say,
「スミス兄弟の体調が心配ですね」
“I am really concerned
about Brother Smith’s health,”
or “Did you hear about Sister Brown’s
experience in the ministry?”
「ブラウン姉妹が伝道で
良い経験をしたのを聞いた？」
これは悪いうわさ話でしょうか
そうではないでしょう
Is this type of gossip harmful?
Generally not.
でも 注意する必要があります
Still, we need to be careful.
テモテ第一 5:13で
At 1 Timothy 5:13,
Paul spoke out against certain sisters
パウロはある姉妹たちが
「うわさ話をしたり
who were “gossipers
and meddlers in other people’s affairs.”
人のことに干渉したりして」いる
と言いました
私たちは人の生活で起きていること
全てを知る必要も
We do not need to know
and share everything we know
about what’s happening
in other people’s lives.
誰かに知らせる必要もありません
スミス兄弟は 自分の病気について
What if, for example,
Brother Smith did not want others
詳しいことを人に知られたくない
と思っているかもしれません
to know details about his health problem?
プライバシーを尊重したいと思います
We need to respect the privacy of others.
Or what if talking
about Sister Brown’s experience turns into,
あるいは ブラウン姉妹の経験を聞いて
こう言う人がいたらどうでしょうか
“Oh, you know, she always brags
about her success in the ministry.”
「姉妹はいつも伝道の成果を
自慢するんだよね」
When our talk about others turns negative,
うわさ話がネガティブな内容になると
中傷に発展しかねません
it can develop into slander.
Slander is making
deliberate, false statements
中傷とは 人の評判を傷つけるために
事実ではない話をすることです
that damage another’s reputation.
Let’s now consider
how harmful gossip wrecks peace.
悪いうわさ話は どのように
平和を壊すでしょうか
あなたが誰かについて悪いうわさ話をし
If you have spread harmful gossip
about someone and he hears about it,
それが相手の耳に入ったとしましょう
when you see him the next time,
その人は次に会う時に
what will be the look on his face?
どんな顔をするでしょうか
ご一緒に格言 25:23を
読んでみましょう
Please read with me Proverbs 25:23:
“The north wind brings a downpour,
「北風は大雨をもたらし
うわさをする舌は怒りを招く」
and a gossiping tongue brings an angry face.”
The north wind in Palestine
パレスチナの北風は
暗い雲と雨をもたらします
brought dark clouds and rain.
Likewise, when the one you gossiped about
あなたが話したうわさが風に乗って
相手に届いたとします
catches wind of this and he sees you,
相手はあなたに会う時
he will have a gloomy, angry face.
暗くて怒った顔をすることでしょう
いわば嵐が生じ
2人の関係は悪化します
There will be a storm
and a chilled relationship.
Now, when that happens,
あなたはどうしますか
you may feel very badly and apologize,
とても後悔し 謝るかもしれません
but you may have damaged his reputation
でも 傷つけてしまった相手の評判は
in a way that may be difficult to undo.
元通りにはならないことがあります
ユダヤ人のこういう昔話があります
Listen to this old Jewish story:
ある男が町の賢人の悪口を
言い触らしました
‘A man went about town
slandering the town’s wise man.
‘Later, the malicious gossiper
realized his wrong
でもその後 うわさ話を
広めたことを後悔し
‘and went to the wise man
and asked for his forgiveness.
賢人に許しを求めに行きました
‘He offered to do
whatever was needed to make amends.
そして 償うために
何でもすると申し出ます
賢人はあることを頼みます
‘The wise man made one request.
‘He told the gossiper
to take a feather pillow,
「枕を切り裂いて中に詰まった
羽根を取り出し
‘cut it open,
and scatter the feathers to the wind.
外にまき散らすように」
と言ったのです
‘Well, the gossiper
was puzzled by this request,
男はそう言われて当惑しましたが
言われた通りにし
‘but he did as instructed.
賢人にこう尋ねます
‘Then he returned to the wise man.
‘“Am I now forgiven?” he asked.
「これで許していただけますか」
賢人は「まず羽根を全部
集めてきてください」と言います
‘“First, go and gather all the feathers,”
the wise man responded.
‘“But, how can I?
「それは無理です 風に
まき散らされてしまいましたから」
‘The wind has already scattered them.”
‘The wise man replied,
賢人は言います
‘“It is as difficult to repair
the damage done by your words
「あなたの言葉によって
傷ついた私の評判も
羽根と同じように
取り戻すことはできません」
as it is to recover the feathers.”’
一度口から出てしまった悪い言葉を
取り戻すことはできないのです
Yes, once spoken,
hurtful words cannot be retrieved.
Let’s not scatter feathers in the wind.
悪い言葉という羽根を
まき散らさないようにしましょう
悪いうわさを広めるなら
If we spread rumors,
it can seriously disturb
the peace of many in the congregation.
会衆の仲間の平和が
壊れてしまうかもしれません
実際に起きたことを
使徒 21:20, 21から見てみましょう
We find an example of this
at Acts 21:20, 21.
エルサレム会衆の長老たちは
パウロに 一部のユダヤ人が
The older men of the Jerusalem congregation
explained to Paul
パウロについてのうわさを広めている
ということを伝えました
that some Jews
had spread a rumor among Jewish Christians
パウロが背教を説き
that he had been teaching an apostasy,
モーセの律法に従わないよう
告げている と言うのです
speaking against the Law of Moses.
もちろん これは事実では
ありませんでした
Of course, this was a twisting of the facts.
パウロは律法に逆らうようなことなど
言いませんでした
Paul never spoke disrespectfully of the Law.
He even went to synagogues
むしろ 会堂でヘブライ語聖書を使って
教えることさえしていました
where he reasoned
on the basis of the Hebrew Scriptures.
Such stories could have led
some newly converted Jewish Christians
改宗してクリスチャンになった
ユダヤ人は
そういううわさを聞いて
パウロが神の取り決めを無視している
と考えたかもしれません
to think that Paul
did not respect God’s arrangements,
もしそういう人がいたなら
会衆の平和は乱されたことでしょう
and this could have seriously disrupted
the peace of the congregation.
In the following dramatization,
次のビデオをご覧ください
notice the effect
that harmful gossip can have
悪いうわさ話は 会衆の平和を
どのように乱すことがあるでしょうか
on the peace in a congregation.
Can you believe that?
あれどうなのかな？
Especially as a pioneer,
開拓者だったら
模範にならないといけないのに
what kind of example is she setting?
エミリーはフォローするの
やめたんですか
Has Emily stopped following her?
No, not yet, but she probably will.
いや でもやめるんじゃないかな
Alistair, what do you think?
アリステア兄弟 どう思います？
About what?
何のことですか
Haley’s posts on QuicPost.
ヘイリーが上げている投稿のことですよ
何か問題があったんですか
Is there a problem?
Emily has told me
エミリーが言うには 全部
they’re all just, “Look at me
「私を見て！私の服
髪 メイク」って感じで
—my clothes, my hair, my makeup.”
And even Celia agrees with her.
セリア姉妹もそう思ってるって
なるほど でもSNSでは
その人の一部しか見えませんよね
Well, it’s very easy to take things
out of context on social media.
私も失敗したことがあります
I know that I’ve done that and realized later
後で 間違いだったと気付いたんです
that I was wrong.
そういうこと ありますよね
Yeah, that’s a good point.
あの ちょっと悪いんだけど
Listen, I don’t want to pull you away,
but if you have a minute, would you mind
giving me a hand with these boxes?
この箱 運ぶの手伝ってもらえるかな
いいですよ
Sure.
助かったよ
Thanks for your help.
No problem.
いえいえ
ジェイク さっきの話なんだけど
心配しているのは分かるよ
Jake, back in the hall,
I know you were just expressing concern,
でも覚えておいてほしいことがあるんだ
but here’s something to consider.
This principle is one of my favorites.
私の好きな聖句なんだけどね
格言 18:17
It’s found at Proverbs
chapter 18 and verse 17.
読んでみて
「最初に言い分を述べる人は
正しく見える
“The first to state his case seems right,
until the other party comes
and cross-examines him.”
やがて相手方が来て 彼に問いただす」
I’m not sure I understand.
どういうことですか
片方の言い分しか聞かないことがある
ということを言っている聖句なんだよ
It just means that sometimes
we only hear one side of a story.
And until we personally hear both,
両方の言い分を聞かないうちに
判断してしまうのは良くないかもね
it’s best not to draw any conclusions.
もし本当だとしても
And even then, if it’s something negative,
ネガティブなうわさは広めたくないよね
we wouldn’t want to spread it
自分もそういうこと されたら嫌だよね
any more than we’d want something spread
about ourselves.
そうやって考えたこと なかったです
I guess I hadn’t considered that.
Thanks.
I’m going to apologize to Harry and Marie
さっきの2人に謝らないと
エミリーにも ヘイリーと話すよう
言ってみます
and have Emily talk directly to Haley.
それがいいね
Good idea.
ジェイクは長老から
格言 18:17に基づく
Did you notice what Jake said
after the elder graciously helped him reason
親切なアドバイスを受けた後
何と言いましたか
on Proverbs 18:17?
「そうやって考えたこと
なかったです」と言いました
He said, “I had not considered that.”
ジェイクはヘイリーについて
ネガティブなことを言う前に
Yes, Jake just did not stop and think
before he said
those negative things about Haley.
少し考えてみるべきでした
So how can we “put away” harmful gossip
では 悪いうわさ話を「脱ぎ捨てる」
には どうしたらいいでしょうか
before it begins?
格言 15:28を読んでみましょう
Let’s read Proverbs 15:28:
「正しい人は答える前に
心の中で思い巡らし
“The heart of the righteous one
meditates before answering,
“but the mouth of the wicked
悪人たちは悪いことを口走る」
blurts out bad things.”
So before we say bad things about others,
誰かについて悪いことを
言いそうになったら
we need to meditate.
考えましょう
No, this does not mean
a long-drawn-out process.
長い時間をかける必要はありません
It just requires a little thought.
ちょっと考えるだけでいいのです
ジェイクは 妻から
ヘイリーの投稿について
What thoughts could have stopped Jake
ネガティブなことを聞かされていました
from repeating his wife’s negative view
of Haley’s post?
でも 聞いたことをみんなに言う前に
He could have asked himself:
こう考えるべきでした
「自分が言おうとしているのは
本当のことだろうか
‘Is what I am about to say true?
これを言うのは親切なことだろうか
‘Is it kind, loving?
‘How will Harry and Marie view Haley
こういうネガティブなことを聞いたら
会衆の人たちはヘイリーのことを
どう思うだろう」
if they hear
those negative things about her?’
悪いうわさ話を脱ぎ捨てる上で
役立つもう1つの原則が
Another principle
that will help us to put away harmful gossip
is the so-called Golden Rule,
ルカ 6:31にあります
as recorded at Luke 6:31.
いわゆる黄金律です
イエスはこう言いました
Jesus said: “Just as you
want men to do to you,
「人からしてほしいと思う通りに
do the same way to them.”
人にもしなさい」
つまり 思いやりを示し
This means showing empathy,
相手の身になって考えるということです
こう考えます
putting ourselves
in the place of the other person,
and asking ourselves,
‘How would I feel
「自分がこういうことを言われたら
if someone said this about me?’
どう感じるだろう」
悪いうわさ話をしたくなるかも
しれない1つの状況は
One situation that may tempt us
to engage in harmful gossip
自分が誰かに傷つけられたと
感じるときです
is when we believe we
have been wronged by someone.
マタイ 5:23, 24や18:15では
Instead of applying the counsel
at Matthew 5:23, 24
and 18:15
まず相手と2人だけで話し合うよう
勧められていますが
to talk to the person privately,
そうせずに関係のない人たちに
話してしまうかもしれません
we could start talking about it
to others who are not involved.
でもその後 相手と話し合ったところ
Imagine if after finally talking
with the person
自分が全く誤解していた
ということに気付きます
you find out he actually
did not wrong you at all.
You will have made the situation much worse.
今となってはもう手遅れです
たとえ自分が正しくても
But whether we are right or wrong,
engaging in hurtful speech
悪いうわさ話をしてしまうなら
will never improve a situation.
状況は悪化するだけです
うわさには話す人と聞く人がいます
Gossip requires a speaker and a listener.
Is it wrong to listen to harmful gossip?
では 聞くだけなら
問題ないのでしょうか
そんなことはありません
格言 17:4にはこうあります
Yes!
Note what Proverbs 17:4 says:
“A wicked man pays attention
to hurtful speech,
「悪人は有害な話に注意を向け
and a deceptive man
listens to a malicious tongue.”
うそつきは悪意ある言葉に耳を傾ける」
Think about that.
ですから 有害で悪意ある
話をする人だけでなく
In God’s eyes if we listen to hurtful,
それに耳を傾ける人も
罪を犯していることになります
malicious speech, we too
bear a heavy responsibility.
By listening to the gossiper,
うわさ話は聞く人がいる限り
広まっていきます
we are encouraging him to go on.
ではどうしたらよいでしょうか
So, what should you do?
「うわさ話は良くない」ときつく言う
代わりに こう言えるかもしれません
Without taking on an air
of self-righteousness,
you could simply say,
“Let’s change the subject,”
「話題を変えましょう」
or “I don’t really feel comfortable
talking about this;
あるいは「その話
私はあまり聞きたくないな
after all, she is not here
to defend herself.”
本人がいない所で話すのはやめよう」
また ある兄弟か姉妹が
And if we find that a brother or sister
うわさ好きであることが分かったなら
likes to gossip,
we may find it easier to avoid harmful gossip
その人と親しく
付き合わないことによって
by stopping close association
with that person.
悪いうわさ話を聞かずに済むでしょう
Proverbs 20:19 frankly counsels:
格言 20:19にはこうあります
“Do not associate
with one who loves to gossip.”
「うわさ好きの人と
交友を持ってはならない」
では兄弟姉妹 悪いうわさ話を
脱ぎ捨てましょう
So, dear friends,
let’s put away harmful gossip.
そうすれば 大切な平和と一致を
守ることができます
Doing so, we will maintain
our precious peace and unity.
Brother Kenneth Cook,
統治体のケニス･クック兄弟が
a member of the Governing Body,
このシンポジウムの最後の話をします
will now present
the final talk of this symposium,
主題は 「平和を壊すものを
『脱ぎ捨てる』 怒り」です
“‘Put Away’ Peace Wreckers
—Uncontrolled Anger.”
Satan is the main peace wrecker.
サタンは平和を破壊します
The Scriptures tell us
that he is driven by “great anger.”
聖書によれば サタンは
「大きな怒り」を抱いています
His anger is malicious and uncontrolled.
悪意があります
怒りを爆発させます
Would any sound-minded,
God-fearing person
神を畏れる私たちが サタンのように
怒りを爆発させることなど
あってよいでしょうか
allow himself
to reflect Satan’s vicious anger?
決してあってはなりません
Of course not!
That is why all true servants of God
are determined
それで私たちは そのような怒りを
「脱ぎ捨てる」よう
to “put away” uncontrolled anger.
努力しなければなりません
But apart from uncontrolled anger,
is all anger bad?
では 怒ることはどんな場合でも
間違っているのでしょうか
The Bible does not condemn all anger.
聖書にはそうは書かれていません
間違っているのは
正当な理由もないのに
It teaches us that anger is wrong
when it is uncontrolled or unjustified.
怒ることや 怒りを爆発させることです
At Ephesians 4:26, God’s Word tells us:
エフェソス 4:26にはこうあります
“Be wrathful, but [it adds] do not sin.”
「腹が立っても
罪を犯してはなりません」
At times, anger
may simply be a strong feeling
これは間違っている と
思うことを目にすると
that comes into us
because of being upset or annoyed
心を乱されたりいら立ったりする
かもしれません
そんな時 怒りを感じることも
あるでしょう
by something that we see as being wrong.
That in itself is not bad.
それ自体は悪いことではありません
But what makes anger bad
is when it fills a person’s heart
避けなければならないのは
怒りの気持ちでいっぱいになり
and he or she just loses control of it.
怒りを制御できなくなることです
When that happens,
そうなってしまうと 冷静に判断したり
行動したりできなくなります
it may cause a person
to act without a sound mind.
Those who continue to lash out in anger
will not gain salvation.
いつも怒りをぶちまける人は
永遠の命を受けられません
Galatians 5:20 lists “fits of anger”
ガラテア 5:19-21によると
among “the works of the flesh”
that will prevent a person
「罪深い欲望から出る行い」をする人は
神の王国を授けられることはありません
from inheriting God’s Kingdom.
There will be no place
for such ones in God’s new world.
「激怒」する人もそうです
新しい世界で生きられません
A brief review of how uncontrolled anger
なぜでしょうか
怒りを制御しないと
wrecks peace for ourselves and others
自分も他の人も平和では
なくなってしまうからです
will highlight why this is so.
Uncontrolled anger
怒りを爆発させると
harms both the angry person
as well as those around him.
その人自身も周りの人たちも傷つきます
We read at Proverbs 29:22
格言 29:22によると
that an angry person “stirs up strife,”
怒りっぽい人は「争いを引き起こし」
adding that he “commits many transgressions.”
「多くの違反を犯」します
そうした違反の1つは
暴言を吐くことです
One of these many sins is abusive speech.
We must work to show restraint
when speaking with workmates,
私たちはさまざまな機会にどう話すかを
意識しなければなりません
with strangers in the ministry,
同僚や伝道で会う人 会衆の兄弟姉妹
with our brothers and sisters
in the congregation,
and with our family members.
家族と話すときなどです
Bad feelings must be controlled.
悪い感情が芽生えたら制御しましょう
Abusive speech, ridicule, contempt,
暴言を吐いたり あざけったり
侮辱したりするのは間違っています
and hateful anger are wrong.
Giving vent to such feelings
can destroy precious friendships
悪感情をあらわにするなら
他の人やエホバとの大切な友情が
壊れてしまうかもしれません
with other people and with Jehovah.
Don’t be like a volcano
that will not quiet down.
噴火し続ける火山のように
なりたいとは思いません
Just like an erupting volcano
will harm those living around it,
噴火する火山は 周囲の人たちに
被害を与えます
so too a person who expresses intense anger
同じように 激しい怒りを
爆発させる人は
will harm those living around him.
周りの人たちを傷つけます
He also damages himself.
自分も傷つきます
なぜそう言えるでしょうか
In what way?
Acting on anger often leads
to even more aggression,
怒りに任せて行動するなら
怒りはさらにエスカレートします
so uncontrolled anger
can also affect our own peace.
そうなると穏やかな気持ちでは
いられなくなります
It can cause us to do something
that we will later regret.
後悔するようなことを
してしまうかもしれません
It can have a negative effect on our health.
健康にも悪い影響が及びます
Medical studies show that uncontrolled anger
医学研究によれば 怒りを
制御しないと血圧が上がり
can cause high blood pressure
and respiratory problems.
呼吸器の問題が生じることがあります
It can also affect the liver and pancreas,
肝臓や膵臓にも影響を与え
and such anger can cause digestive problems.
消化器系の問題が生じることもあります
When a person becomes angry,
頭に血が上ると
he or she will not always think clearly.
冷静に考えることができなくなります
激しく怒った後 気分が
落ち込んでしまう人もいます
After a fit of rage,
a person may become depressed.
No wonder we read at Proverbs 14:30
格言 14:30にある通りです
that “a calm heart gives life to the body.”
そこには 「穏やかな心は
体に良」い とあります
The disastrous consequences
of uncontrolled anger
怒りを爆発させると
どんな結果になるでしょうか
are illustrated in God’s Word
聖書の例を見てみましょう
by the actions of Simeon and Levi,
族長ヤコブの息子
シメオンとレビの行ったことです
sons of the patriarch Jacob.
When they learned that their sister, Dinah,
2人は妹のディナがシェケムに
犯されたことを知った時
was violated by a man named Shechem,
we read at Genesis 34:7
創世記 34:7にある通り
that “they were offended and very angry.”
「不快に思い 憤慨し」ました
怒りを抱く正当な理由がありましたが
Now, they had a valid reason to be angry,
but they took their anger too far.
行き過ぎた行動をしてしまいました
怒りを爆発させたのです
It was uncontrolled.
Simeon and Levi
took vengeance on Shechem.
シメオンとレビは
シェケムに復讐しました
Using deception, they attacked and killed
シェケムの町の人たちをだまして
そこに住む男たちを皆殺しにしました
every male in Shechem’s city.
Then, along with the other sons of Jacob,
その後ヤコブの他の息子たちは
町の物を奪い
they plundered it and took
the women and little children captive.
女性や小さな子供たちを捕らえました
Dinah’s tragic experience
must have grieved Jacob greatly.
そのことを知ったヤコブはとても悲しみ
心痛を味わいました
Yet, he condemned
his sons’ uncontrolled anger.
息子たちが怒りに任せて
行動したことを責めました
Simeon and Levi
tried to justify their actions,
シメオンとレビは自分たちのしたことを
正当化しようとしました
but that was not the end of the matter,
でも エホバも2人の行動を
不快に思いました
because Jehovah was also displeased.
For this reason, Jacob later foretold
ヤコブは後に神からの導きを受け
that the descendants of Simeon and Levi
シメオンとレビの子孫が
were to be scattered
among the tribes of Israel.
イスラエルの中で散らされる
と予告しました
Their uncontrolled anger brought disfavor
2人が怒りに任せて行動したことを
神もヤコブもとても不快に思いました
from God and from their father, Jacob.
We’re wise to pay attention
to such Scriptural accounts
聖書のこうした例をよく学び
怒りを脱ぎ捨てるのは大切なことです
and put away uncontrolled anger
and all of the harm that it brings.
そうすれば 悪い結果を
身に招くことはないでしょう
In the following dramatization,
次のビデオをご覧ください
notice how a person
might be tempted to give in to anger.
怒りを制御しないとどうなってしまうか
学ぶことができます
おばあちゃん
Yes, Nana?
卵忘れないでね
Don’t forget eggs, dear.
No, no, I didn’t forget.
ああ覚えてる 覚えてる
Are you sure, love?
大丈夫？
うん 大丈夫
No, I won’t forget. OK.
ありがとう
Thank you so much.
うん じゃあまたね
OK. Love you.
Bye.
ああ！
No!
Haley, finally, I’ve caught you.
ヘイリー やっと話せた
ちょっといい？
Do you have a minute?
ああ エミリー 後でもいい？
今朝はいろいろあって
Hi, Emily.
Can we talk later?
I’m really struggling this morning.
ヘイリーいつも忙しそうにしてるから
いつ話せるかなと思ってたんだけど
You know, it’s just that you’ve been so busy,
and I’ve been waiting for the right moment;
I’d really just like to address it.
どうしても話したいことがあって
分かった 何？
OK. What’s up?
It’s just that I’ve noticed
your posts lately on QuicPost.
この間上げてた投稿のことなんだけど
What about them?
それが何？
Well, do you really think they’re something
that a pioneer should be posting?
開拓者なのにあんなの上げて
大丈夫なのかな と思って
What? What are you talking about?
何？何が言いたいの？
Some people might think you’re bragging.
自慢してると思われてるみたいよ
Some people? What people?
何それ？誰が？
仕事で商品見せてるだけなのに
It’s a business account.
I’ve got to show off my products.
そう そうなんだけど
I know. I get that.
It’s just—
I don’t know.
自分に注意引こうとしてるんじゃ
ないかって思ってる人もいるよ
It could feel like you’re drawing
a little too much attention to yourself.
Who would think like that? You?
誰が言ってるの？エミリーでしょう？
違う 私だけじゃないよ
セリア姉妹もだよ
No, not just me; Celia felt the same.
セリア姉妹にも話したんだ！
You spoke to Celia about this?
そんなに怒らないで ジェイクが・・・
I didn’t want to upset you.
Jake said that I needed to take . . .
ジェイクも！みんなが私のこと
良くないって言ってるの？
Jake! So everyone thinks
my posts are inappropriate?
Not everyone, Haley.
違うよ みんなじゃないよ ヘイリー
そういうことじゃなくって
That’s not what I am saying at all.
そういうとこ あるよね
ほんと信じらんない
You are such . . .
Wow! I can’t believe you.
ほかに誰に話したの？
ほんとうわさ好きだよね
Who else have you spoken to?
You are just such a gossip!
うわさなんかしてない
I’m not gossiping. I was trying to . . .
You are!
してるじゃない！
I’m just trying to help you,
if you would just listen to me.
私はただヘイリーのためを思って
言っているだけ
言いたいだけでしょ！
You’re so jealous!
話を聞いてってば
If you’d just listen to me.
ちゃんと聞いてますけど
Oh yeah, listen to this.
そんな人だと思わなかった
And I expected more from you.
ヘイリー 何があったの？
Haley, what are you talking about?
うわさしてたでしょ！私の投稿のことで
Gossiping about my posts!
Are you that lonely
that you’ve got nothing better to do?
さみしいからって
ほかにすることないんですか？
ヘイリー
Haley,
wait, please!
ねえ ちょっと待って！
見ていてはらはらしましたね
Were you left feeling a bit tense?
If so, you know
what uncontrolled anger can lead to.
きっと この後どうなって
しまうんだろうと思ったことでしょう
Now that we’ve defined uncontrolled anger
ここまでで 怒りを制御しないなら
and considered what it can lead to,
どんな結果になるかを考えました
the next question is,
次に考えたいのは
How can we put away uncontrolled anger?
どうすれば怒りを
脱ぎ捨てられるかということです
First, we need to recognize
the danger of uncontrolled anger.
まず 怒りにはどんな危険が潜んで
いるかを理解する必要があります
Proverbs 25:28 states
格言 25:28にはこうあります
that “as a city broken through,
without a wall,
「怒りを抑えられない人は
is the man who cannot control his temper.”
城壁のない打ち破られた町のようだ」
Strong city walls
were vital in ancient times.
昔 城壁は大切な役割を果たしました
城壁がなければ 敵がすぐに
侵入してきたでしょう
Without them a city
would quickly fall to invaders;
likewise, so will those
who cannot control their temper.
怒りを抑えられない人も同じです
By losing control, they
make themselves vulnerable
かっとなると心が無防備になり
間違った考えが入ってきてしまいます
to the invasion of wrong thoughts
—thoughts that can cause them
to hurt themselves and others.
そうした考えは自分や
他の人を傷つけかねません
Uncontrolled anger can do just that.
怒りを抑えないと
そういうことになるのです
Next, after recognizing the danger,
危険を理解することに加えて
どんなことが必要でしょうか
we must pause and then deal with the anger
怒りを感じたら 何かを言ったり
したりする前に少し考えましょう
before it causes us
to do something that we will regret.
When anger grows within us,
怒りが込み上げてきたら
we’re wise to recall
what happened with Simeon and Levi.
シメオンとレビのことを
思い出してください
We might also recall what happened
先ほど見たビデオで
どんなことが起きていたかを
in the video dramatization
that we just viewed.
思い出すこともできます
You see, in each case,
どちらの場合も 怒りに任せて
行動する前によく考えていれば
pausing before reacting out of anger
may have spared
much pain and heartache, true?
大変な結果にはならなかったはずです
That is why we have this warning
格言 17:14もこう勧めています
at Proverbs 17:14:
“Before the quarrel breaks out,
take your leave.”
「言い争いになってしまう前に
そこを去れ」
With that in mind,
each of us should ask himself:
それで 次の点を自問しましょう
「全てを知っているわけではないのに
‘Do I tend to jump to conclusions
決め付けてしまうところがあるだろうか
‘when I don’t have all the facts?
‘If so, can I take my leave
and put away anger
怒りが募る前に
そこを去って気持ちを静めることが
できるだろうか」
before it starts to build up?’
The inspired advice
ヤコブ 1:19のアドバイスは
found at James 1:19 will help us to do so
怒りを抑える助けになります
私たちみんなが一生懸命に努力して
当てはめたいアドバイスです
—but only if we make
a sincere and determined effort
to apply what it says.
読んでみましょう
Let’s read that verse—James 1:19.
ヤコブ 1:19です
And here we find some simple steps
ここには怒りを脱ぎ捨てる上で役立つ
幾つかのことが書かれています
to help us put away uncontrolled anger.
It says: “Know this, my beloved brothers:
「覚えておいてください 皆が
人の言うことに進んで
耳を傾けるべきです
“Everyone must be quick to listen,
slow to speak, slow to anger.”
すぐに話したり すぐに怒ったり
してはなりません」
If we ask Jehovah to help us with this,
人の言うことに「進んで耳を傾け⋯⋯
すぐに話したり
すぐに怒ったりし」ないよう
namely to “be quick to listen,
slow to speak, slow to anger,”
エホバに祈って助けを求めましょう
he will assist us to do so.
エホバは私たちが状況をよく理解し
He will help us
to see the facts of the matter,
思いやりを示し 怒りを
脱ぎ捨てることができるよう
show understanding,
and then put away uncontrolled anger.
助けてくださるでしょう
A word of caution, though:
もう1つ大切なのは
To succeed in doing our part,
良い友達を選ぶことです
we must choose our associates wisely.
このことが大切なのはなぜでしょうか
We could undermine all of our good work
これまで どんなに頑張って
エホバに助けてもらいながら
and Jehovah’s help in controlling our anger
怒りを制御してきたとしても
if we choose associates who are arrogant,
高慢で 頑固で
すぐに怒る人と付き合うなら
opinionated, or quick to become angry.
努力が水の泡になってしまうからです
Regarding someone who is disposed to rage,
格言 22:25には
Proverbs 22:25 warns:
激怒しやすい人の「行いを
まねるようになっては
ならない」とあります
“Never learn his ways.”
Well, we’ve enjoyed
another outstanding series of talks
私たちはこの大会のプログラムを通して
that should help us to keep awake,
警戒を怠らず 立派な行動を続け
maintain fine conduct,
and escape the judgment
that will soon come on this world.
新しい世界で生きるのに
必要なことを学んでいます
As this symposium has emphasized,
そしてこのシンポジウムでは
we must do our utmost
to continue to put away peace wreckers
平和を壊すものを脱ぎ捨てる努力を
続けるよう励まされました
such as inappropriate boasting, envy,
その中には 自慢 ねたみ 不正直
dishonesty, harmful gossip,
悪いうわさ話 怒りなどがあります
and uncontrolled anger.
If we have a problem
with any of the peacemaking qualities
自分が何かの点で改善しなければ
ならないことに気付くなら
that we have discussed in this symposium,
エホバに助けを求め
seek Jehovah’s help
to change and then work at it.
一生懸命に努力し
変化するようにしましょう
Our sincere efforts to pursue peace
では 兄弟姉妹と平和な関係を
築くよう真剣に努力しましょう
with our brothers and our sisters
will influence how earnestly
we are awaiting “Jehovah’s day”
「エホバの日」と新しい世界を心から
待ち望んでいる人はそうするはずです
and his promised new world.
Yes, our genuine efforts
will affect our hearts
天のお父さんエホバは
私たちの誠実な努力に
目を留めてくださいます
and will be noticed by our heavenly Father.
Then, in his great mercy,
これからも エホバとの
そして仲間との平和な関係を
築いていきましょう
Jehovah will consider us
to be, as his Word says,
“spotless and unblemished and in peace”
そうすれば 憐れみ深いエホバは
私たちを「汚点も傷もない平和な人」
と見てくださるでしょう
—both with him
and with our fellow worshippers.
Thank you, brothers, for helping us
to strengthen our bond of unity.
一致の絆を強めるのに役立つ話を
ありがとうございました
Since the rebellion in Eden,
エデンでの反逆以来
peace among mankind as a whole
has been lost.
人類の間には
ほとんど平和が見られていません
でもエホバは ご自分に頼る人たちに
Despite this, Jehovah has given peace
平和を与えてこられました
to those who trust in him.
How has he done so in the past,
過去にどのように
そうしてこられましたか
そのことは今どのように
信仰を強めるでしょうか
and how does this strengthen
our faith in him today?
We invite you to enjoy Part 1
of the documentary
ではこれから
「エホバは平和へと導いてくださる」
Jehovah Guides Us in the Way of Peace.
第1部が始まります
どうぞご覧ください
Our military forces are committed to peace.
We have chosen peace.
Our wish, our prayer, is for peace.
We yearn for peace.
We pray for peace.
For thousands
人間はこれまでずっと
平和を願ってきました
of years, humans have tried
to find peace
—peace as individuals,
一人一人の平和
peace as families,
家族の平和
peace for the entire human race.
全人類の平和です
We want to lay the foundation of peace
for generations to come.
We want to do the hard work now
so our children and our grandchildren
can grow up in a peaceful world.
The future we want:
opportunity and security for our families,
a rising standard of living,
a sustainable, peaceful planet for our kids
—all that is within our reach.
Yet, despite humans’ best efforts,
人間は平和のために
いろいろな事をしてきましたが
peace
どれもうまくいっていません
has been elusive.
For millenniums,
何世紀にもわたって指導者たちは
rulers and governments
have tried to achieve peace
平和のために 条約を結んだり
through treaties,
resolutions,
決議を採択したり 会談を開いたりし
summits
and, ironically, war.
皮肉にも戦争さえしてきました
人類の平和は今
Our peace as humans
is more fragile than ever.
かつてないほど脅かされています
Man’s efforts to bring about lasting peace
平和を実現するための人間の試みは
have failed time and time again.
何度も何度も失敗してきました
This isn’t surprising to us.
これは驚くようなことではありません
Jeremiah 10:23 tells us:
エレミヤ10章23節にあるように
“It does not belong to man . . .
to direct his step.”
「人は⋯⋯自分で自分の歩みを
導くことが」できません
元々 人間が人間を治めることには
無理があるのです
Humans were simply not designed
to rule themselves.
健康 安全 安心感
Good health, safety, overall well-being
これらは聖書が言う
「終わりの時代」が進むにつれて
—these are becoming harder to find
as we move further into what the Bible
ますます失われていっています
refers to as “the last days.”
As long as human rule continues,
人間が人間を治める限り
争いや対立は無くなりません
disunity will continue.
It’s true that global peace
どんなに努力しても 人間の力では
世界を平和にはできません
cannot be obtained by human efforts alone.
でも 神との絆があれば
安心して暮らすことができます
But those who are close to God
can find peace of mind right now.
Isaiah 48:17, 18 says:
イザヤ48章にはこうあります
「私エホバは あなたの神である
“I, Jehovah, am your God,
あなたのためになる生き方を教え
“the One teaching you to benefit yourself,
あなたを導いて正しい道を歩ませる
“the One guiding you
“in the way you should walk.
あなたが私のおきてに
注意を払いさえすれば！
“If only you would pay attention
“to my commandments!
そうすれば あなたの平和は
川の流れのように豊かにな［る］」
“Then your peace
would become just like a river.”
It’s only Jehovah
人類を導いて
世界を平和な場所にできるのは
who has the ability to guide humans
to real, lasting peace.
エホバだけです
そうエホバは約束しています
He promises he will bring this about.
Until this happens,
その時が来るまで安心して暮らせるよう
Jehovah continues to provide ways
エホバは私たちを助けてくれます
どのようにしてでしょうか
for us to experience peace now.
How does he do that?
「人間の理解をはるかに超え」た
By giving us “the peace of God
that surpasses all understanding.”
「神からの平和」を
与えることによってです
平和が失われそうに
なったことがあるのは
We aren’t the only ones
whose peace has been challenged.
God’s Word is filled
with accounts of faithful servants
現代の私たちだけではありません
聖書には同じような経験をした人が
たくさん出てきます
whose peace was challenged
by the dominating forces of their day.
As we study and meditate on these accounts,
その人たちがどのようにエホバに頼り
助けてもらったかを考えると
the lessons we learn from them
私たちを平和へと導いてくださる
エホバへの信頼が強まります
help us to trust in Jehovah
as he guides us to peace.
そういう記録は
Understanding how these accounts
relate to Jehovah’s purpose to bring peace
エホバが神の王国によって実現させる
平和と関連があります
by means of his Messianic Kingdom
gives us confidence
エホバが私たちを必ず助け
that his purpose never fails
平和へと導いてくださるという
確信を持たせてくれます
and he will support
and guide us on into the future.
One of Jehovah’s prophets
そうやってエホバに
助けてもらった人の1人に
who learned this lesson firsthand was Jonah.
ヨナがいます
ヨナは紀元前9世紀の預言者です
Jonah lived in the ninth century B.C.E.
Jehovah assigned Jonah to go to Nineveh,
ヨナはエホバから アッシリア帝国の
都市ニネベに行くようにと言われます
a city of the Assyrian Empire.
Based on what he knew about Nineveh,
ニネベがどんな都市かを知っていたので
Jonah considered this to be
ヨナは恐れと不安で
いっぱいになりました
an intimidating and threatening assignment.
The Assyrians were known as fierce warriors,
アッシリアの兵士たちは
残虐なことで知られ
and Nineveh itself was later described
ニネベは後に「流血に満ちた都市」
と呼ばれるようになりました
as a “city of bloodshed.”
それで 異教の神を信じる人たちに
So you can understand Jonah’s trepidation
when Jehovah asks him
都市の滅亡を知らせるように
と言われた時
to proclaim a judgment message
against this imposing city
ヨナが恐怖に襲われたのもうなずけます
and its pagan inhabitants.
何とか身を守るために
In an attempt to find peace,
Jonah decides to go far away from Nineveh
ヨナはニネベから
遠く離れた所に行こうとし
and boards a boat headed for Tarshish.
タルシシュ行きの船に乗ります
タルシシュは 現在のスペインに
あったと考えられています
Tarshish is generally associated
with modern-day Spain.
それでイスラエルから見ると
So from Israel,
this is the complete opposite direction
ニネベとは全く逆の方向に
行ったことが分かります
of Nineveh.
でも 身を守るどころか
Jonah found anything but peace.
かえって危険にさらされます
うわあ！
Look!
船長！
まずいな
By the gods.
Furl the sail!
帆をたため！
これは普通の嵐ではありませんでした
Now, this was no ordinary storm.
猛烈な雨風にさらされ
It was so severe that the ship
船は沈みそうになりました
was in danger of being wrecked.
Captain, we’re taking on too much water!
船長！水が大量に入ってきます
これは神々のたたりだ！
This storm is from the gods!
バアルよ！
Baal!
Eshmun!
エシュムン様！
船員たちは自分の神に呼び掛けますが
ヨナは分かっていました
The crew cried out to their gods,
but Jonah knew the true Source of the storm.
これはエホバだと
And now he accepts
それで責任を感じ
自分のせいだと打ち明けます
personal responsibility for the situation.
Lift me up
私を持ち上げて海に投げ込めば
and throw me into the sea,
and the sea will calm down for you;
静まるでしょう
for I know that it’s because of me
この大嵐が生じているのは
私のせいだと分かっているからです
that this violent storm has come upon you.
そうやって自分から名乗り出るためには
Can you imagine the courage it took
相当の勇気が必要だったはずです
for Jonah to make this request?
He had no way of knowing
if Jehovah would save him,
エホバが助けてくれるかどうかは
分かりませんでした
でも 自分のせいで人が死ぬのは
耐えられませんでした
but he did not want others
to perish on his account.
エホバはヨナを思いやり
助けの手を差し伸べます
In his mercy, Jehovah spares Jonah’s life.
どうしてまだ生きてるんだ？
How am I still alive?
What will become of me?
私はどうなるんだろう？
When faced
難しい任務を前にして
with a difficult assignment,
ヨナはエホバから逃げて
タルシシュに行こうとしました
Jonah “got up to run away from Jehovah
to Tarshish.”
ヨナの良心は痛み始めます
Jonah’s conscience had to bother him;
こんなことをして本当に
良かったのだろうか
he had to be questioning his decision.
He tried to take matters into his own hands,
自分で何とかしようとしてしまいました
自分で自分の身を守ろうとしました
tried to find his own peace.
その結果 今どこにいるでしょうか
Where does he find himself?
魚の腹の中です
In the belly of a fish!
Yet he calls to Jehovah
in a moment of despair.
ヨナは悔いる気持ちで
エホバに助けを求めます
エホバよ
O Jehovah,
out of the depths of the Grave,
シェオルの腹の中から
助けを叫び求めます
I cry to you for help.
Please hear my voice.
私の声を聞いてください
自分の誓約したことを
What I have vowed, I will pay.
私は果たします
ヨナはもうエホバの預言者として
Jonah could have reasoned
that this was the end
of his assignment as Jehovah’s prophet.
務めを果たすことはないと
思ったかもしれません
何しろ 指示に従いませんでした
After all, he did disobey direction.
それでエホバから
もう一度指示があった時
So likely, he was surprised
to hear the word of Jehovah come to him
とても驚いたことでしょう
a second time.
Jonah!
ヨナ！
Get up,
立って 大いなる都市ニネベに行き
go to Nineveh the great city,
and proclaim to her
私があなたに語る布告をふれ告げよ
the message that I tell you.
Yes.
はい 分かりました
ありがとうございます
Thank you.
最初ヨナは自分で何とかしようとし
At first, Jonah trusted in himself
and didn’t understand
エホバが残虐なアッシリア人から
守ってくれるとは考えませんでした
that Jehovah would protect him
from the violent Assyrians.
But after being given
a second chance, what happens?
では 2回目はどうだったでしょうか
Well, then he puts aside
あれこれと心配するのはやめて
his human concerns
エホバが守ってくれると
信じて行動しました
and looks to Jehovah for protection.
あとわずか40日で ニネベは倒される
In just 40 days more,
Nineveh will be overthrown.
まことの神エホバは言われた
Jehovah, the true God, has spoken.
This city will be destroyed.
この都市は滅ぼされる
Nineveh will be overthrown.
ニネベは倒される
The true God will overthrow Nineveh.
まことの神はニネベを倒される
まことの神は言われた
The true God has spoken.
やがて 王自ら心を入れ替え
Eventually, the king himself repents
and orders everyone
ニネベの人たちにも同じように
するようにと命令を出します
in Nineveh to do the same.
Jonah learned a valuable lesson
この出来事からヨナは
大切なことを学びました
from this experience.
By originally running away from Nineveh,
最初はニネベから逃げて
エホバを信頼するのではなく
he chose to trust in himself
rather than putting his trust in Jehovah.
自分で何とかしようとしました
Are you Jonah?
あなたがヨナですか
I am.
そうだよ
ママはあなたのおかげだって言ってた
Mommy says you saved us.
いや エホバのおかげだよ
No, Jehovah saved you.
私はただ
I was just—I was just a messenger.
言われたことを伝えただけだ
ヨナは学びました
Jonah learned
エホバを信頼して言われる通りに
すれば 必ず守ってもらえます
that without a doubt
Jehovah protects those
who trust and obey Him.
私たちの場合も同じです
If Jehovah has asked you to do something,
エホバから 「これをやってみなさい
if he’s asked me to do something,
こちらに進みなさい」と言われる時
if he’s leading us,
he absolutely will guide us through it.
エホバは必ず道を切り開いてくれます
Jonah’s account proves this.
そのことを確信できます
ニネベの人たちは心を入れ替えたので
Although the Ninevites were spared
because they repented (that’s true),
この時は救われましたが
Assyria later
アッシリアはやがて
再び悪い道に進むようになります
returned to its evil, wicked ways.
About a century
ヨナの時から約1世紀が過ぎ
after Jonah’s judgment message,
アッシリアの王セナケリブは
King Sennacherib of Assyria brought
ユダの町々に次々と攻め入ります
his armies against the cities of Judah,
including the city he wanted most
目指すはエルサレムの陥落です
—Jerusalem.
King Hezekiah of Judah
ユダのヒゼキヤ王は
was an outstanding king
「エホバにしっかり」従う
素晴らしい王でした
who “held fast to Jehovah.”
王になった最初の頃から
From the beginning of his reign,
ユダだけでなくイスラエル全体で
he proved to be zealous for true worship
正しい崇拝を熱心に広めました
not only in Judah but in all of Israel.
ヒゼキヤはエホバの崇拝のために
力を尽くしてきましたが
Hezekiah had done so much
to stand up for pure worship,
今や セナケリブの軍隊により
yet now he is faced with the prospect
of a siege against Jerusalem
エルサレムは侵略の危機に面しています
by Sennacherib’s armies.
ヒゼキヤは平和のために
Hezekiah agrees to pay Sennacherib
セナケリブの要求に応じて
金銀を支払います
a tribute in return for peace.
Yet, the armies continue their conquests,
しかし セナケリブは侵略を続け
as Sennacherib and his men besiege
強固に防備された町
ラキシュを包囲します
the strongly fortified city of Lachish.
セナケリブはそこから軍隊の一部と
長官たちをエルサレムに送り
From here,
Sennacherib sends a part of his army
as well as military chiefs to Jerusalem
降伏を迫ろうとします
in an attempt to demand surrender.
代表して話すのは ヘブライ語を
上手に話せるラブシャケです
The spokesman for the group was the Rabshakeh,
who spoke Hebrew fluently.
ラブシャケは大声でヒゼキヤをののしり
エホバをあざけります
He loudly ridiculed Hezekiah
and taunted Jehovah,
「エホバなどセナケリブ王の前では
全くの無力だ」と言います
boasting that Jehovah
was no match against King Sennacherib.
聞いていた兵士たちがどう思ったか
考えてみてください
Imagine what these soldiers
must have been thinking.
Sennacherib’s armies were on a warpath,
セナケリブの軍隊は ほかの町を
次から次へと攻め取っています
taking city after city.
ヒゼキヤはどうするか
決めなければいけません
To Hezekiah, this was a defining moment.
自分の力で何とかするでしょうか
He had to decide if he would trust in himself
それとも エホバの力を
信頼するでしょうか
or trust in Jehovah.
My brothers,
エホバは過去と同様
we must remember that Jehovah
私たちを助けることも
十分にできるのです
is fully able to rescue us,
just as he has in times past.
ヒゼキヤ王！
God’s Word . . .
King Hezekiah,
まだ現実が見えないのですか
will you not even now face the facts?
We are trapped!
わなに掛かった鳥のようです
The Assyrians are at our gate,
あなたは何も悪いことは起きない
という考えにしがみついている
and you cling to the belief
that nothing bad will happen.
You will destroy everything
あなたは神殿やエルサレム
you so hope to preserve
そして私たちを
滅ぼそうとしているのです
—the temple, Jerusalem,
our very lives.
私は危険を理解していますし
恐れてもいます
Shebna, I am not blind
to the dangers that we face.
I too am afraid.
もしエホバがエルサレムの滅びを
許されるなら それでもよいのです
But if Jehovah
allows Jerusalem to fall,
so be it.
しかし 私たちがエホバのものを
どうして引き渡せるでしょうか
How can we give up what belongs to Jehovah?
ヒゼキヤはエホバの力を
信じることにしました
So as a man of faith,
Hezekiah focused on Jehovah’s ability
たとえセナケリブの軍隊が
エルサレムに向かってきているとしても
to save His people
despite Sennacherib’s
continued advances toward Jerusalem.
エホバなら救うことができる
と考えました
私はおまえたちの王に興味があるんだ
I’m curious about this king of yours.
彼は誰が私から救い出してくれる
と思っているのかね
Who does he think
will come to save him from me?
おまえたちの神 エホバは弱いんだ！
Jehovah, your God,
is weak!
He will cringe before my god Asshur.
エホバも私の神 アシュルの前で
縮み上がっているんだろう
Hezekiah remained
ヒゼキヤはエホバを信頼
し続けることにしました
determined to trust in Jehovah.
This decision required
a tremendous amount of faith,
そうするには相当の信仰が
必要だったはずです
especially with more than
何しろ18万5000人以上もの
アッシリア軍が
185,000 Assyrian soldiers
エルサレムに向かってきているのです
headed toward Jerusalem.
いつ攻撃されても
おかしくない状況でしたが
Instead of trusting in himself,
he continued to look
ヒゼキヤは自分で
何とかしようとするのではなく
for Jehovah as the Source of true peace
安心を求めてエホバに頼り続けました
even as an attack seemed imminent.
エホバはこのたびも どんなに強い
人間の王たちであっても
And Jehovah again
showed just how insignificant
エホバの前では何の力も
ないことを証明します
human rulers are in comparison to him.
Hezekiah learned
ヒゼキヤはもう駄目だと
思えるようなときでも
that when a way out seems impossible,
エホバを信頼するなら必ず
道が開けることを学びました
trusting in Jehovah always leads to success.
エホバはアッシリア軍を打ち破り
信頼に応えてくれました
Jehovah rewarded that trust
with victory over the Assyrians.
This is a lesson
we can apply now and in the near future.
これは私たちもずっと
覚えておきたいことです
今も 将来もです
この先 危険な目に遭うことが
あるかもしれません
There may be situations
when true worshippers seem trapped,
でも 忘れてはいけません
but never forget
that Jehovah is all-powerful.
エホバに不可能なことはありません
エホバは導いてくれます
He’s leading his people,
信頼して しっかり付いて
いくことが大切です
and we can follow
his guidance with full confidence.
そうすれば エホバは
ハルマゲドンの時に守ってくれます
Jehovah will protect those
who trust in him at Armageddon.
Jerusalem remained safe
エルサレムはこのたびは
敵の攻撃から守られましたが
against attack for the time being,
平和な時期は長くは続きませんでした
but peaceful conditions didn’t last long.
Hezekiah’s son Manasseh
ヒゼキヤの子マナセは エホバから見て
忌まわしいことを行いました
did what was detestable
in the eyes of Jehovah.
バアル崇拝を復興させたばかりか
He brought back Baal worship
and personally took its vilest practices
それをより大々的に行い
to extremes,
異教の彫刻像をエホバの
神殿の中に置くことさえしました
even putting a carved image of a false god
right inside Jehovah’s temple.
少し考えてみてください
So here you have a king
本来なら間違った崇拝から
国民を守るべき王が
who’s supposed to be protecting
the people from idolatrous influence
正反対のことをし
異教の神の祭壇を作っています
doing the exact opposite
—building altars to false gods.
しかも自分の子供たちを火で焼いて
He even went so far
as to pass his own sons through the fire,
異教の神に犠牲として
捧げることさえしました
sacrificing them to these gods.
The peace with God that Hezekiah
ヒゼキヤが国民のために
築き上げた神との平和な関係が
worked so hard to achieve for the nation
今やその息子によって
壊されてしまいました
is now reversed by the actions of his son.
Because of this,
それでエホバはマナセを
厳しく処罰します
Jehovah punished Manasseh severely.
He allowed the king of Assyria
マナセはアッシリアの王に捕らえられ
バビロンに連れていかれます
to take him captive to Babylon.
While in captivity,
マナセは牢屋の中で
心から悔い改めました
Manasseh ultimately repented.
心を入れ替え その後はずっと
エホバだけを崇拝するようになりました
He humbled himself,
and he stayed faithful
right to the end of his life.
おじいちゃん！
Grandfather!
エホバだけを崇拝することが
どれほど大切かを
We can imagine him impressing
the importance of faithfulness
孫のヨシヤにしっかり
教えたことでしょう
to Jehovah on his young grandson Josiah.
Listen to me.
話したいことがある
Jehovah is holy,
エホバは聖なる方で
and you must serve him
おまえはエホバが望まれる仕方で
the way he wants us to.
ただエホバだけに仕えなければならない
All other gods
ほかの神には何の力もない
are powerless.
Yet, in spite of all this,
それにもかかわらず 人々はまだ
the people still thought
エホバとバアルの両方に
仕えられると考えています
that they could serve Jehovah and Baal.
So after becoming king,
それで ヨシヤは王になった後
偶像崇拝根絶のために動き出します
Josiah started a campaign against idolatry.
よそじゃもっと安かったぞ
I’ve seen these cheaper.
Take it or leave it.
買わないならいいわよ
We start here!
ここからだ！
No!
ワーッ！
この国の偶像は全てこうなる
This is what we will do to every false god in the land.
ヨシヤは異教の祭壇を取り壊し
He tore down altars used for false worship,
聖木や偶像を打ち砕きました
sacred poles, images, and statues.
国から偶像崇拝を一掃するためです
He was intent
on cleansing the land of idolatry.
Now, he showed remarkable courage
偶像崇拝がはびこる中で
真の崇拝のために恐れることなく
勇気を出して立ち上がりました
to stand up for true worship
at a time when few were doing so.
決して簡単なことではありませんでした
There’s no doubt this was a difficult task.
これでよいのだろうか と
不安になることもあったでしょう
At times, he may have even wondered
if he was doing the right thing.
おそらくエホバは預言者エレミヤを
通して ヨシヤを励ましたことでしょう
It’s possible Jehovah provided Josiah
with assurance from the prophet Jeremiah.
エホバはこう言っている
This is what Jehovah says: “Look!
「ヨシヤという男の子が
ダビデ家に生まれる
“A son named Josiah
“will be born to the house of David!
“He will sacrifice on you
その人は 高い場所の祭司たちを
あなたの上で犠牲として捧げる
“the priests of the high places,
“those making sacrificial smoke on you,
あなたの上で犠牲の煙を
立ち上らせている祭司たちをである」
and he will burn human bones on you.”
That prophecy
300年以上前に語られた
この預言の言葉は
made over 300 years earlier confirmed
紛れもなくヨシヤこそが
that Josiah was the one
prophesied to act against false worship.
間違った崇拝を終わらせる
王であることをはっきり示していました
This may have given Josiah
even greater incentive and courage
それでヨシヤは これでいいんだと思い
ますます自信を持って 神殿の修復
などの改革を進めたはずです
to continue his campaign,
which now included repairing the temple.
These actions contributed
そのおかけでエホバだけが
崇拝されるようになり
to the peaceful conditions
that elevated pure worship.
平和な時代がやって来ました
エホバのために一生懸命だった
ヨシヤに私たちは引かれます
Josiah did so much
to restore pure worship.
That is why we love him.
でも 人々の心は腐りきっていて
Yet, the peoples’ heart condition
remained polluted,
厳しい処罰がどうしても必要でした
so the nation required severe discipline.
ユダはバビロニア人に征服される
とエレミヤは預言しました
Jeremiah prophesied
a conquest of the Babylonians
against Judah.
All this land
この土地は荒廃する
will be reduced to ruins,
and this land and its inhabitants
あなたたちは70年の間
バビロンの王に仕えなければならない
will have to serve the king of Babylon
for 70 years.
エレミヤがそう預言するのを
ダニエルも聞いたかもしれません
Daniel himself may have heard
Jeremiah speak those words.
And he certainly
預言はその通りになり 自分も家族も
バビロンに連れていかれました
saw it come true as he and his family
were exiled to Babylon.
不安でいっぱいだったはずです
Talk about peace being interrupted!
ダニエルは将来を
期待される若者でしたが
Daniel was a young Judean prince taken
連れてこられ 家族からも
引き離されました
from his homeland
and separated from his family.
しかも ネブカドネザル王の宮廷で
But being chosen to receive special training
特別な訓練を受けることになり
in the court of King Nebuchadnezzar
不安はいっそう募ります
presented another set of challenges.
バビロニア人の生活は
The entire way
ダニエルが育ったユダでの生活とは
まるで違っていました
of Babylonian life was contrary
to what Daniel knew growing up in Judah.
でも ダニエルは エホバが
禁じた食べ物で
But Daniel was determined
not to pollute himself
自分を汚すことはしない
と決意していました
with foods Jehovah would not approve of.
And Jehovah blessed
そうやって頑張るダニエルを
エホバは後押しし
Daniel’s determination to be faithful,
as he was selected to serve
ダニエルは王の下で働く
賢人の1人に選ばれます
as one of King Nebuchadnezzar’s wise men.
ネブカドネザルは国々を攻め取って
大帝国を築こうとしていました
Nebuchadnezzar was a warrior-king
intent on building a great empire.
紀元前624年に王位に就いてから
After he officially
took the throne
in 624 B.C.E., his domain
侵略を続け 領土を
広げていっていました
grew with each conquest.
Babylon became an epicenter
of trade and commerce.
バビロンは貿易と商業の
中心地になっていました
Nebuchadnezzar undertook
王は都市の周りに 強固な城壁を築き
huge building projects throughout the city,
今やバビロンは難攻不落に思えました
which made the city seem impregnable.
バビロンに住んでいた人たちは
Imagine the sense of security
the inhabitants of Babylon must have felt,
こんな城壁に囲まれていれば絶対に
安心だと思っていたことでしょう
locked safely behind the city’s walls.
Nebuchadnezzar
ネブカドネザルは都市の
繁栄と安全は全て
attributed the prosperity
and security all around him
自分の神々のおかげだ
と考えていました
to the power of his false gods.
The chief of these false gods
was Marduk, the god of war.
そのうちの一番の神は
戦争の神マルドゥクでした
でも そうした神々や祭司たちは
全く無能でした
Yet, these false gods and their priests
would prove to be worthless.
One night,
ある夜 ネブカドネザル王は
奇妙な夢を見ます
King Nebuchadnezzar had a strange dream.
Call the wise men!
賢人たちを呼べ！
王が生き続けますように
どのような夢かお話しください
O king, may you live on forever.
Relate the dream to your servants.
そうすれば解き明かします
We will tell the interpretation.
No!
なんだと！
If you don’t make the dream known to me
もしおまえたちが夢の内容を話さず
解き明かさないなら
along with the interpretation,
you’ll be dismembered,
手足を切り取って おまえたちの家を
公衆便所にしてやる
and your houses will be turned into public latrines.
無理です そんなこと誰にもできません
There is not a man on earth
who can do what the king demands.
What the king is asking is difficult.
難し過ぎます
No one exists
who could tell this to the king except
王に説明できるのは 神々だけでしょう
—except the gods.
Seize them!
捕らえろ！
処刑しろ！
Kill them!
エラハ
Jerah.
逃げてください
You’re in danger.
何かあったのか？
Why? What happened?
I didn’t hear everything,
詳しくは分かりませんが 賢人たちが
王の逆鱗に触れて 明朝処刑されます
but the wise men angered the king.
Everyone is to be executed by dawn.
Bring Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah here.
ハナニア ミシャエル アザリヤを
連れてきてください
I’ll try to learn more.
相談します
This edict to kill all the wise men
王が出したこの命令によれば
ダニエルと仲間たちも
殺されることになります
would also include Daniel and his companions.
So let’s look at this
from Daniel’s perspective.
この時 ダニエルは
どう感じたでしょうか
Here he is, a young man in a foreign land,
若くして異国の地に連れてこられ
serving in the court of one
of the most powerful and violent men alive.
世界で最も権力のある残忍な王の
宮廷で仕えています
その王がとんでもない
無理難題を吹っ掛けてきます
And that man is now demanding
that someone, in effect, read his mind:
「誰かいないのか
夢の内容を話せ
“Tell me my dream,
意味を解き明かせ」
and tell me what it means.”
王よ
O king,
interpretations belong to my God, Jehovah.
私の神エホバなら解き明かせます
王が見た夢と その意味を
He knows your dream and what it means.
じゃあ おまえの神の言葉を聞かせろ！
Well, where is your God?
Where?
エホバはきっと
I believe that he—
I know that he will reveal it to me.
いや必ず夢を解き明かしてくださいます
どうか時間をください
Please, give me time.
Daniel is not acting
ダニエルは経験があったので
そう言ったのではありません
on previous experience.
He hasn’t received interpretations
of dreams from Jehovah.
これまでエホバから夢の解き明かしを
受けたことはありません
彼を動かしていたのは信仰でした
Instead, he is acting on faith
—faith that he had learned
当時読めた聖なる書物を
学ぶことによって得た信仰です
by studying the sacred books of his time.
These books
そうした書物の中には モーセ ダビデ
likely included the inspired writings
of Moses, David, Solomon, Isaiah,
Jeremiah, and other prophets.
ソロモン イザヤ エレミヤなどが
書いた書物があったはずです
Oh, we can only imagine
ダニエルはきっと そうした巻物を
真剣に読んでいたことでしょう
Daniel poring over these scrolls,
心からエホバに祈り 知恵と理解を
与えてくださいとお願いしたはずです
opening up his heart to Jehovah,
begging Jehovah to give him wisdom and understanding.
He loved it.
とても大切な時間でした
There’s no doubt that
そうやって神の言葉を学ぶことにより
as Daniel studied these accounts,
ダニエルの信仰は強まりました
his faith was strengthened
and his bond with Jehovah drew even closer.
エホバとの絆もますます深まりました
So even though Daniel knew nothing
of King Nebuchadnezzar’s dream,
ネブカドネザル王の夢について
何も知りませんでしたが
ダニエルは確信していました
he was fully convinced
それがどんな夢で どんな意味が
あるかをエホバが教えてくれて
that Jehovah would reveal the dream
and its interpretation
命を救ってくれることを
and prove to be Daniel’s salvation.
ダニエルはこの時 聖書の
どの書物を調べたのでしょうか
Do we know exactly which accounts
Daniel was able to draw from at this time?
It’s impossible to say for a certainty,
ダニエル書によれば 少なくとも
幾つかの書物を参照することが
できたようです
but we do know he had access to “the books.”
エレミヤの書物への言及があります
He references the prophecies of Jeremiah.
エホバに頼った人たちがどのように
助けてもらったかを学びました
Daniel could see how Jehovah blessed
faithful, obedient men in the past.
So by asking Nebuchadnezzar for time,
それで 時間をくださいと言ったのは
命を少しでも伸ばそうと
したからではありません
he wasn’t looking to buy himself
another day of life;
he was allowing Jehovah to reward his faith
エホバが信頼に応えて
夢を解き明かしてくれると
信じていたからです
by revealing the dream to him.
ダニエルはただ信じただけでは
ありませんでした
Daniel strikes a balance here.
エホバが必ず夢の解き明かしを
してくれると確信していましたが
Although he is confident
that Jehovah will reveal the dream to him,
he isn’t casual in the way
he handled the situation.
何もせずに成り行きに任せるような
ことはしませんでした
He did what any God-fearing man
エホバに心から祈りました
would do here.
神に仕える人みんなにとって
素晴らしい手本です
He approached Jehovah in prayer.
O Jehovah,
エホバ ここに来たのは
死ぬためではないはずです
surely you didn’t bring us here just to die.
この国の人たちはどう思うでしょうか
What will people say?
We told them
あなたが天の神で
that you are the God of the heavens,
秘密を明らかにする本当の神だと
言ってしまいました
the only God who can reveal secrets.
どうか 力をお示しください
Please, vindicate yourself.
ユダで捕らえた人の中で王の夢を
解き明かせる者を見つけました
I have found a man from the exiles of Judah
who can make known
the interpretation to the king.
誰かは分かっている
I know who he is.
おまえは本当に私が見た夢の内容を話し
Can you really make known to me
the dream that I saw
解き明かせるのか
and its interpretation?
There is a God in the heavens
秘密を明らかにされる神が
天におられます
who is a Revealer of secrets,
その方が 最後の日々に起きる事柄を
and he has made known to King Nebuchadnezzar
what is to happen
ネブカドネザル王に知らせたのです
in the final part of the days.
This is your dream:
これが あなたが見た夢です
王は巨大な像をご覧になりました
You saw an immense image.
That image
その像があなたの前に立っていました
was standing in front of you.
You yourself are the head of gold.
あなたこそが金の頭です
あなたの後に 劣った別の王国
But after you another kingdom will rise,
銀のものが生じます
inferior to you.
Then another kingdom, a third one, of copper,
次いで別の王国
3番目の銅のものが生じ
that will rule over the whole earth.
全世界を支配します
As for the fourth kingdom,
4番目の王国は 鉄のように
強いものとなります
it will be strong like iron.
The kingdom will be divided.
この王国は分裂することになります
And as the toes of the feet
足の指には鉄の部分と
粘土の部分があるので
were partly of iron and partly of clay,
この王国には強い部分と
もろい部分があることになります
so the kingdom will be partly strong
and partly fragile.
ダニエルがこうするには 相当の
信仰と勇気が必要でした
This took a tremendous amount of faith
and courage on the part of Daniel.
私たちも不安に襲われることや
Now, we may find our peace threatened,
命が危うくなることが
あるかもしれません
our very lives might be on the line.
In that moment, we can turn
to Jehovah God in prayer,
そういう時 ダニエルのように心から
エホバに祈りたいと思います
opening up our hearts,
confident that he will support us.
助けてくれると信じて祈ります
私たちもダニエルとヨナと同じような
任務をエホバから受けています
Like both Daniel and Jonah,
we’ve been given an assignment
to proclaim a message.
This requires courage to speak out boldly
神を認めようとしない人たちが
どうなるかをはっきり伝えるのは
concerning Jehovah’s judgments
とても勇気のいることです
against those who oppose his sovereignty.
この2人の預言者から
Both of these prophets are excellent examples
エホバを信頼すれば必ず助けて
もらえるということが分かります
of Jehovah backing those who trust in him.
私たちが信仰を捨てない限り
Jehovah will always be with us
as long as we have faith in him.
エホバはいつもそばにいてくれます
When we face situations that seem impossible,
たとえヒゼキヤのように絶体絶命だと
思える状況になったとしても
as in the case with Hezekiah,
we have the ability to tap
どんな力よりも強い聖なる力を
エホバからもらうことができます
into the most powerful force there is!
この体制の終わりが近づくにつれ
As this system comes to a close,
we will find ourselves in situations
私たちの勇気が試されたり
平和が脅かされたりする時が必ず来ます
that test our courage and threaten our peace.
エホバを揺るぎなく
支持しなければいけません
We will have to stand up
for pure worship
ヨシヤのようにです
just like Josiah, and this will be unpopular.
周りはそうしないかもしれません
But with Jehovah on our side,
でも エホバが共にいてくれるので
we can face those situations with confidence.
どんなことがあっても大丈夫です
He’s all-powerful,
誰よりも強いエホバが助けてくれます
and he’s going to help us through it.
Now, here’s the interesting thing:
注目したいことがあります
Some of the prophecies that Daniel recorded
ダニエルが書いた預言の言葉は
バビロニア帝国がどうなるかだけを
明らかにしていたわけではありません
applied not only to the future
of the Babylonian Empire
その後から現代に至るまで
but also outline world events
そして将来世界がどうなるかも
明らかにしていました
to our day and beyond.
And these events are being fulfilled
その予告されていたことが
実際に起きているのを
今 私たちはこの目で見ています
right before our very eyes!
考えさせられる内容でした
What a motivating presentation!
平和が脅かされる時も
Even when our peace is threatened,
自分の忠誠がエホバの目的と
どう関係するかに注意を集中し
we can focus on how our integrity
relates to Jehovah’s purpose,
and we can endure with joy.
そして喜びを持って
忍耐することができます
大会の3日目午後の部分で
見ることができる
We look forward to watching Part 2
of this important consideration
第2部の内容も本当に楽しみです
during the final session of our convention.
では ご一緒に130番の歌
Now let’s sing together song number 130,
「進んで許す」を歌いましょう
entitled “Be Forgiving.”
歌は130番です
That’s song number 130.